<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Reading Lists on Beng Tan</title>
    <link>https://bengtan.com/reading-list/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Reading Lists on Beng Tan</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-au</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 09:00:00 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://bengtan.com/reading-list/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Reading List (2021-04-01)</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/reading-list/20210401/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 09:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/reading-list/20210401/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;h2 id=&#34;technical&#34;&gt;#technical&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://fasterthanli.me/articles/pin-and-suffering&#34;&gt;Pin and suffering&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021) — A different kind of tutorial about async Rust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to think that my understanding of &amp;ldquo;async Rust&amp;rdquo; has increased over the past year or so. I&amp;rsquo;m 100% onboard with the basic principle: I would like to handle thousands of concurrent tasks using a handful of threads. That sounds great!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://arctype.com/blog/json-in-postgresql/&#34;&gt;Forget SQL vs NoSQL - Get the Best of Both Worlds with JSON in PostgreSQL&lt;/a&gt; (Jan 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn how to use JSON with PostgreSQL to create a schema for any situation. Follow examples of storing JSON data, querying it, and avoiding anti-patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://mbuffett.com/posts/qr-code-hitchhikers-guide/&#34;&gt;How Much of the Hitchhiker&amp;rsquo;s Guide to the Galaxy Can You Fit on a QR Code?&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been dealing with QR codes recently, as one of my side projects generates them, and I got curious about how much data you can really fit in a QR code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://thenewstack.io/souped-up-gopher-project-geminis-plan-to-revolutionize-internet-browsing/&#34;&gt;Souped-Up Gopher: Project Gemini’s Plan to Revolutionize Internet Browsing&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A team of highly motivated and principled developers is quietly building an entirely new web of content, served by different servers and accessed with an entirely new kind of software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://adamzerner.bearblog.dev/think-like-an-educator-about-code-quality/&#34;&gt;Think like an educator about code quality&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been said a thousand times: code is for humans to read, not for machines to execute. However, writing code that is easy for humans to read is much easier said than done. It&amp;rsquo;s something that takes years to learn, and decades to master.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I might be able to offer a shortcut though: think like an educator about code quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;science&#34;&gt;#science&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-00782-w&#34;&gt;First known gene transfer from plant to insect identified&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discovery that a whitefly uses a stolen plant gene to elude its host’s defences may offer a route to new pest-control strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://phys.org/news/2021-03-ancient-genomes-decline-scythians.html&#34;&gt;Ancient genomes trace the origin and decline of the Scythians&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally thought of as fierce horse warriors, the Scythians were a multitude of Iron Age cultures who ruled the Eurasian steppe, playing a major role in Eurasian history. A new study published in Science Advances analyzes genome-wide data for 111 ancient individuals spanning the Central Asian Steppe from the first millennia BCE and CE. The results reveal new insights into the genetic events associated with the origins, development and decline of the steppe&amp;rsquo;s legendary Scythians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencealert.com/the-shifting-hues-of-sleeping-octopuses-indicate-a-second-sleep-state&#34;&gt;We Have The First-Ever Confirmation of Alternating Sleep States in an Octopus&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flickering colors of a sleeping octopus seem to indicate something akin to an REM sleep state, scientists have found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, as octopuses snooze, they distinctly cycle between two major sleep states, quiet and active. This discovery suggests not only that an active sleep state evolved separately in vertebrates and cephalopods, but also that, just like terrestrial vertebrates, octopuses might be able to dream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://bollu.github.io/mathemagic/jacobian/index.html&#34;&gt;The Jacobian, geometrically&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, I&amp;rsquo;m going to motivate a geometric quantity known as the Jacobian you may have seen in multivariable calculus. It shows up without explanation when one solves multiple integrals; little explanation is given to what it means . At the end of reading this, if you knew what a Jacobian is, you&amp;rsquo;ll have a sense of what it really means. If you didn&amp;rsquo;t, even better &amp;mdash; you&amp;rsquo;ll learn what the Jacobian is!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2021/mar/26/california-condor-reintroduced-yurok-tribe&#34;&gt;Endangered condors return to northern California skies after nearly a century&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a century of absence, the endangered California condor is set to return to the skies of the Pacific north-west.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The condor once soared from British Columbia to Mexico, but habitat loss, overhunting and, most significantly, poisoning from hunting ammunition drove the birds to near extinction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencealert.com/giant-demon-ducks-of-doom-had-to-squish-in-their-brains-despite-their-massive-heads&#34;&gt;These Huge &amp;lsquo;Demon Ducks&amp;rsquo; With Squished Brains Were an Extreme Evolutionary Experiment&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back when mega wombats, sheep-sized echidnas, and marsupial lions roamed the ancient lands of Australia, there also lived a gigantic flightless bird. Known by some as the &amp;lsquo;demon duck of doom&amp;rsquo;, Dromornis stirtoni is described by paleontologist Trevor Worthy as an &amp;ldquo;extreme evolutionary experiment&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;life&#34;&gt;#life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://levels.io/contact-me/&#34;&gt;Why I&amp;rsquo;m unreachable and maybe you should be too&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021) — A good problem to have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may have noticed it&amp;rsquo;s practically impossible to contact me. I did that on purpose so I can spend my time how I want to spend it. I don&amp;rsquo;t really use email and I have my private message inboxes on every platform closed. And they have been like that for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://smarter.blog/always-be-writing/&#34;&gt;Always be writing&lt;/a&gt; (Feb 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always be writing, if possible everyday, and if possible on the internet for everyone to read. Writing is a valuable skill worth cultivating. It helps you think better, opens up new opportunities for yourself, and others will benefit from your writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2021/03/numtot-tinder-dating-site-transit-nerds/618434/&#34;&gt;There’s a Better Way to Date Online — If You Like Trains&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inside NUMTinder, a Facebook dating group exclusively for people who are really into public transit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wired.com/story/sleep-procrastination-psychology-tips/&#34;&gt;Why You Stay Up So Late, Even When You Know You Shouldn’t&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are certain traits that lend themselves to &amp;lsquo;revenge bedtime procrastination&amp;rsquo;. There’s also a way out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;random&#34;&gt;#random&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;http://bentilly.blogspot.com/2010/08/analysis-vs-algebra-predicts-eating.html?m=1&#34;&gt;Analysis vs Algebra predicts eating corn?&lt;/a&gt; (Aug 2010)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like learning about odd connections between disparate things.  This probably is the oddest example that I know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.spectator.co.uk/article/the-beauty-of-the-ampersand-and-other-keyboard-symbols&#34;&gt;The beauty of the ampersand and other keyboard symbols&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Claire Cock-Starkey’s guide to glyphs and punctuation marks is, by turns, scholarly, poetic, philosophical and funny&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jdawiseman.com/PricingMoney.html&#34;&gt;Pricing Money: the whole book&lt;/a&gt; (Nov 2019) — The text of Pricing Money, J. D. A Wiseman, Wiley (2001) with some updates from 2019. Off-topic but may be useful for some.&lt;/p&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reading List (2021-03-29)</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/reading-list/20210329/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2021 12:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/reading-list/20210329/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;h2 id=&#34;technical&#34;&gt;#technical&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2021/03/29/what-data-cant-do&#34;&gt;What Data Can’t Do&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever you try to force the real world to do something that can be counted, unintended consequences abound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;once a useful number becomes a measure of success, it ceases to be a useful number. This is known as Goodhart’s law, and it reminds us that the human world can move once you start to measure it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uzbek cotton pickers, judged on the weight of their harvest, would soak their cotton in water to make it heavier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;when America’s first transcontinental railroad was built, in the eighteen-sixties, companies were paid per mile of track. So a section outside Omaha, Nebraska, was laid down in a wide arc, rather than a straight line, adding several unnecessary (yet profitable) miles to the rails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numbers don’t lie, except when they do. Harford is right to say that statistics can be used to illuminate the world with clarity and precision. They can help remedy our human fallibilities. What’s easy to forget is that statistics can amplify these fallibilities, too. As Stone reminds us, “To count well, we need humility to know what can’t or shouldn’t be counted.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://brianschrader.com/archive/why-all-my-servers-have-an-8gb-empty-file/&#34;&gt;Why All My Servers Have an 8GB Empty File&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021) — Even if this isn&amp;rsquo;t for you, it&amp;rsquo;s still a brilliant example of lateral thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of last year, all of my servers have an 8GB empty spacer.img file that does absolutely nothing except take up space. That way in a moment of full-disk crisis I can simply delete it and buy myself some critical time to debug and fix the problem. 8GB is a significant amount of space, but storage is cheap enough these days that hoarding that much space is basically unnoticeable&amp;hellip; until I really need it. Then it makes all the difference in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.thea.codes/opinions-after-a-decade/&#34;&gt;Opinions after a decade of professional software engineering&lt;/a&gt; (Feb 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code isn&amp;rsquo;t even close to the most important thing about software engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Software and software engineering are inherently political.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Communication skills and empathy are the most important skills for any engineering discipline. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter how brilliant you are if you can&amp;rsquo;t understand the needs of others, can&amp;rsquo;t communicate your ideas, and can&amp;rsquo;t work with other people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is our moral responsibly to create and use technology to empower instead of oppress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being involved with a community is the best way to grow and learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; and others&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/BBVA/kapow&#34;&gt;https://github.com/BBVA/kapow&lt;/a&gt; — Convert internal server or network data into a HTTP API. Duct tape for the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.cryptohack.org/twitter-secrets&#34;&gt;Recovering a full PEM Private Key when half of it is redacted&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021) — Do not share private information online. Partial redaction is not safe. You have been warned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.ohmysmtp.com/blog/your-emails-are-not-gdpr-compliant/&#34;&gt;Your emails are probably not GDPR compliant&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021) — Spy pixels!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;indie-biz&#34;&gt;#indie biz&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@ErezDruk/a-simple-recipe-for-startup-execution-2706a8f894cf&#34;&gt;A Simple Recipe for Startup Execution&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021) — Crystallise your priorities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Execution = Speed * Focus * Prioritization (or SFP)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speed — learn as fast as possible by iterating as fast as possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus — do one hard thing at a time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prioritization — work on what’s most important right now&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bluelabellabs.com/blog/how-much-does-it-cost-to-make-an-app-in-2021-infographic/&#34;&gt;How Much Does it Cost to Make an App in 2021? [Infographic]&lt;/a&gt; — The numbers aren&amp;rsquo;t as interesting as pointing out that development is just one step of many.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://javierfuent.es/blog/Lessons-promoting-side-project/&#34;&gt;What I learned promoting my first side project as an engineer&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resources I found useful&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Screely: A really simple and easy way to make the screenshots of your product look good. I used it for the product hunt launch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CodeImg: Same idea as screely but for code. I used it for the Twitter thread where I explained how I built it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diagram of product hunt launch: A great overview with all the rules of thumb when launching in Product Hunt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Photopea: Free simpler version of photoshop in your browser. I used it to create a simple logo and to add text to the screenshots from screely.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;copy.ai: GPT-3 powered copywriting. It helps to brainstorm different ways you can communicate your product. I used it to get ideas for the product hunt description.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;science&#34;&gt;#science&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nationalgeographic.com/science/article/scientists-spot-a-space-hurricane-for-the-first-time&#34;&gt;Scientists spot a &amp;lsquo;space hurricane&amp;rsquo; for the first time&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An international team of scientists may have finally figured it out. These spots could be the northern lights rotating in an unorthodox spiral shape similar to the familiar shape of a hurricane—a phenomenon the team has dubbed a “space hurricane.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But finding just one is exciting enough for now. “As humans, we think we know a lot about the universe and our own planet and what is around us,” Oksavik says. “And then we discover something we didn’t expect.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://ai.facebook.com/blog/ai-names-colors-much-as-humans-do/&#34;&gt;AI names colors much as humans do&lt;/a&gt; (Mar, 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the way we use words to represent different colors is remarkably consistent. For example, many languages have two distinct words for red and orange, but no language has many distinct commonly used words for various tonalities of orange.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;cutting-edge AI systems behave similarly. When &amp;hellip; tasked with creating a way to communicate &amp;hellip; what colors they see, they develop systems that balance complexity and accuracy much as people do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also found that &amp;hellip; to be an optimal solution, it must use discrete symbols rather than continuous sounds. &amp;hellip; Is it possible that our languages can be optimally structured only if they are made up of discrete symbols rather than, say, continuous whistling?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;life&#34;&gt;#life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://savvytokyo.com/ikigai-japanese-concept-finding-purpose-life/&#34;&gt;Ikigai: The Japanese Concept Of Finding Purpose In Life And How This Age-Old Ideology Can Help You Find Happiness&lt;/a&gt; (Jan 2020)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter ikigai, the age-old Japanese ideology that’s long been associated with the nation’s long life expectancy. A combination of the Japanese words “iki” (生き), which translates to “life,” and “gai” (甲斐), which is used to describe value or worth, ikigai is all about finding joy in life through purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://param.codes/2021/notetaking/&#34;&gt;Notetaking for fun and profit&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing things down helps me remember things better because it means that I’m not endlessly consuming words, I’m also producing something, even if it is just a few sentences rephrasing the text I read. Once you produce something about a topic, you know it much better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting benefit I’ve had with writing notes is that the &lt;em&gt;amount&lt;/em&gt; of content I produce has quite dramatically increased. &amp;hellip; I write a lot more. &amp;hellip; I have a feeling the archive will be quite valuable to me a few years down the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;random&#34;&gt;#random&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⭐ &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.macrumors.com/2021/03/24/steve-jobs-employment-questionnaire/&#34;&gt;Job Application Filled Out by Steve Jobs in 1973 Sells for $222,400&lt;/a&gt; (Mar 2021) — Quick! Burn it and sell the NFT!&lt;/p&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reading List (2021-03-25)</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/reading-list/20210325/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 12:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/reading-list/20210325/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;A great breakdown (for the semi-technically inclined) of &lt;a href=&#34;https://wasteofserver.com/nft-exactly-as-they-are/&#34;&gt;what an NFT is&lt;/a&gt; (⭐⭐⭐⭐⭐) and a possible reason &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nateliason.com/blog/nft-value&#34;&gt;why NFTs are valuable&lt;/a&gt; (⭐⭐⭐⭐).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who would have thought that a &lt;a href=&#34;https://creatorcollabhouse.substack.com/p/how-ben-collins-built-a-google-sheets&#34;&gt;blog about Google Sheets could have 400k views per month&lt;/a&gt; (⭐⭐)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fun primer into &lt;a href=&#34;https://tonsky.me/blog/emoji/&#34;&gt;how emoji&amp;rsquo;s work&lt;/a&gt; (⭐⭐⭐⭐⭐) underneath (It&amp;rsquo;s more complicated than you thought). Every programmer needs to read this and know what a grapheme cluster is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A scary and sobering &lt;a href=&#34;https://michelenasti.com/2021/01/28/no-sight-developer.html&#34;&gt;interview with a developer who is losing his sight&lt;/a&gt; (⭐⭐⭐). Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t wish it on anyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone wanna &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Daniel-Liu-c0deb0t/uwu&#34;&gt;uwu-ify text&lt;/a&gt; (⭐⭐⭐⭐)? (Warning: Extreme humour ahead.) But what does &lt;a href=&#34;https://studybreaks.com/tvfilm/the-origin-of-the-word-uwu/&#34;&gt;uwu&lt;/a&gt; (⭐⭐⭐) mean?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mccormick.cx/news/entries/what-i-learned-bootstrapping-side-projects-in-2020&#34;&gt;What I learned bootstrapping side projects in 2020&lt;/a&gt; (⭐⭐)&lt;/p&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reading List (2021-02-12)</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/reading-list/20210212/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 12:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/reading-list/20210212/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;Some stuff I found on the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ignorethecode.net/blog/2021/02/02/switching_to_windows/&#34;&gt;Switching to Windows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Lukas Mathis (ignorethecode.net)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A software engineer and usability expert realises that Windows suits him better and lists the tips and tweaks that ease him in the transition from MacOS to Windows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interesting comment: &amp;ldquo;a lot of people seem to be making the switch now&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://marcel.is/1password/&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m glad for using 1Password&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Marcel Krčah (marcel.is)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The author documents two instances where using a password manager saves him by:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preventing a phishing attack, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Limiting the damage of a compromised password.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.potaroo.net/ispcol/2021-02/iot.html&#34;&gt;The Internet of Trash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Geoff Huston (potaroo.net)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The chief scientist of APNIC foreshadows the long term problems caused by obsolescence and lack of software updates for hardware devices. He suggests there is market failure in dealing with this and that regulation may be needed to solve it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scottberkun.com/2021/put-faith-in-ux-design/&#34;&gt;How To Put Faith in UX Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Scott Berkun (scottberkun.com)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TBH, didn&amp;rsquo;t really read this through.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just read it for the parts (and pictures) about anglerfish (eww!!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Males of the species, who are much smaller, lack a functioning digestive system. To survive they must combine, or fuse-mate, with the females. &amp;hellip; And when each male latches on, it slowly loses organs it no longer needs. It loses its eyes and its fins, its kidneys, even its precious heart gets reabsorbed into its new host. It is no longer a creature itself. It is just a sexual appendage.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://timkellogg.me/blog/2021/01/29/cold-paths&#34;&gt;Cold Paths&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Tim Kellogg (timkellogg.me)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A deep insight into the nature of some rare bugs with suggestions for how to avoid them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;A cold path is a path through the code or situation that rarely happens. By contrast, hot paths happen frequently. You don’t find bugs in hot paths.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interesting and thought-provoking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://abarry.org/dna-sequencing-in-our-extra-bedroom/&#34;&gt;Sequencing DNA in our Extra Bedroom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Andrew J Barry (abarry.org)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A hilarious story about a robotics engineer who buys a USB DNA sequencer as a Christmas gift for his (genetics PhD) girlfriend and the trials and tribulations they have to go through in order to try it out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After two or more days, the sequencing results indicate that they are &amp;ldquo;hosting viruses that are preying on the bacteria we&amp;rsquo;re also hosting.&amp;rdquo; Ew!!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Funny and a great light read.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.awaxman.com/beware-the-cult-of-numeracy&#34;&gt;Beware the Cult of Numeracy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Adam Waxman (blog.awaxman.com)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A contrarian view about (over-)use of data and analytics in decision-making.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;the proliferation of data is putting more and more attention on short term and easy to measure metrics. In the short run this leads to stellar &amp;hellip; updates. However, in the long run it often frustrates users, depletes trust, and reduces brand loyalty.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bautista.dev/remote-salaries/&#34;&gt;What Companies Get Wrong about Remote Salaries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Eduardo Bautista (bautista.dev)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A freelance software engineer in Mexico has his view on salaries at companies who hire remotely.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;I have learned that there are two types of companies that hire remotely. The first type looks to hire engineers at a cheaper rate. The second type wants to hire the best engineers. Be the latter.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://milachervenkova.rocks/blog/how-to-sell-niche-website/&#34;&gt;I Sold 2 Niche Websites from My Portfolio (and I learned something)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Mila Chervenkova (milachervenkova.rocks)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A multi-entrepreneur talks about her story of selling two niche websites from her portfolio. Both sites sold for about 2-3 times yearly earnings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A good behind-the-scenes account with lots of details.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
