<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on Beng Tan</title>
    <link>https://bengtan.com/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Beng Tan</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-au</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2021 12:00:00 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://bengtan.com/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>App Startup vs Content Startup</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/blog/app-startup-vs-content-startup/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2021 12:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/blog/app-startup-vs-content-startup/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;Here is something that occurred to me recently. It&amp;rsquo;s not a law or anything, but just a thought-provoking observation. I find it interesting, and maybe it&amp;rsquo;s useful as a tool in thinking about startups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most startups are either an &lt;strong&gt;app startup&lt;/strong&gt; or a &lt;strong&gt;content startup&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do I mean? Let&amp;rsquo;s back up a bit and talk about definitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I say &amp;lsquo;startup&amp;rsquo;, I don&amp;rsquo;t mean a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.paulgraham.com/growth.html&#34;&gt;company that is designed to grow fast&lt;/a&gt;. I mean any venture that is new (and, in the context of this discussion, usually related to tech).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An app startup (where &amp;lsquo;app&amp;rsquo; == &amp;lsquo;application&amp;rsquo; and doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean just smartphone apps) is something that sells a technology (or an integration of existing technologies). It allows users to do something new, or do something in a faster, better or cheaper way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A content startup is something that sells content, or sells the ability to interact with other people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With definitions out of the way, let me repeat the above statement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most startups are either an app startup or a content startup.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, in truth, all businesses do a bit of both, but usually, a startup is dominated by one or the other. Hence, conceptually, most startups can be classified as one or the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Note that I said &amp;lsquo;most&amp;rsquo;, not &amp;lsquo;all&amp;rsquo;. This is just a heuristic, and sometimes heuristics break down.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Off the top of my head, here are some &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;App startups&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google search&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Android&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tesla&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open AI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Substack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WordPress, Ghost, or any other CMS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These startups produce and/or sell a technology. Usually, the technology is novel or not easy to reproduce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Content startups&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BetaList&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product Hunt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stratechery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Substack newsletter writers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone who sells eBooks, courses, or newsletters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tech media ie. Engadget, Techmeme etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone who sells themes or plugins for WordPress or another CMS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AirBnB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Twitter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Content startups utilise known technology. Their technology is reproducible but the value of the startup is not in the technology. Instead, the hard-to-reproduce part is in the content side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, it&amp;rsquo;s not hard to recreate the functionality of BetaList, Product Hunt or Stratechery, but it is much harder to duplicate the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, anyone can sell WordPress themes online. However, it&amp;rsquo;s much harder to create themes that people want to buy and to generate enough marketing and exposure to consistently get new buyers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, anyone can create an AirBnB or Twitter clone, but they&amp;rsquo;d be useless without a community of users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What startups can you think of? Are they app startups or content startups?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bonus/trick question: Can you think of any startups which aren&amp;rsquo;t easily classified by this distinction?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;* * *&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s the point of thinking of startups as either app or content?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it&amp;rsquo;s fun and frivolous theorising and it could be a useful aid in thinking about startups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me personally, it leads to a very important and relevant insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that &amp;hellip; people who are makers/builders tend to build app startups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(What about the reverse? Do non-technical founders tend to build content startups? Um, I don&amp;rsquo;t know. Maybe this is a question for a future article.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I like building things. As a developer/maker/hacker/whatever, I always gravitate towards app startup ideas. I instinctively try to build some cool new tech. I have never, in the past, considered content startup ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a blind spot. It&amp;rsquo;s a very big blind spot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am unconsciously cutting myself off from half of the market of startup ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yikes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All those stories about people who produce courses on how to use the next hip new tech stack and sell for thousands of dollars per month? I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be able to conceive doing something similar because I&amp;rsquo;ve blinded myself to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily for me, I&amp;rsquo;m aware of this now. Hopefully it&amp;rsquo;s not going to limit me any more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about you? If you are also a maker/hacker and you only consider app startup ideas, are you also limiting yourself?&lt;/p&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A New Beginning</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/blog/a-new-beginning/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2021 12:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/blog/a-new-beginning/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;This blog represents a new beginning and I&amp;rsquo;m both excited and trepidatious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, I&amp;rsquo;ve considered blogging at one time or another over the last 15-20 years, but I&amp;rsquo;ve always been too busy with more important or fun &amp;lsquo;stuff&amp;rsquo;. Everytime I think about it, it sounds like a great idea &amp;hellip; and then it fizzles out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a history of building things. Software/tech/web things that are supposed to make money. Call them micro-startups or side projects or lifestyle businesses or whatever. I&amp;rsquo;ve done a smattering of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from jobs and freelancing gigs, I would spend my discretionary time on building something &amp;hellip; that I hoped would make money. It&amp;rsquo;s great fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except when they don&amp;rsquo;t make money. Then it&amp;rsquo;s just a time sink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the things that I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to monetise, sometimes the results were modest. Other times, the results were mediocre or downright terrible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my most recent project, I wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gigobooks.com&#34;&gt;non-subscription accounting app&lt;/a&gt; for people with gigs or simple affairs. I had a lot of fun writing it. And I use it for myself (ie. dogfooding) too. Awesome!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve spent the better part of nine months building it and I&amp;rsquo;ve shipped the MVP. Problem is &amp;hellip; Where are my users?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uh, oh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s happened again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I built something. And the users aren&amp;rsquo;t coming. Even worse, this time, they don&amp;rsquo;t even know about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have tried to get some word out and I&amp;rsquo;ve posted on various forums over the Internet. I&amp;rsquo;ve got a tiny trickle of people who visit the website and then, AFAICT, don&amp;rsquo;t come back. That&amp;rsquo;s about it. No one (other than myself) is actually using the app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Granted, I didn&amp;rsquo;t spend a lot of time doing &amp;lsquo;marketing&amp;rsquo; things, but I did spend &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; time, and the results have been underwhelming. It also doesn&amp;rsquo;t help that I have no pre-existing audience. No blog, no twitter followers. Nada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Distribution is a hard problem. Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s sometimes even harder than writing software. Lack of distribution has killed my previous projects before. Several times. If I don&amp;rsquo;t solve this problem, it&amp;rsquo;s going to kill this latest project too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I took a step back and thought about things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;* * *&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I need to learn how to do distribution. And marketing and all that other stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can build things, but if I can&amp;rsquo;t reach users, then what&amp;rsquo;s the point?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my to-do list of marketing activities, I had &amp;lsquo;content marketing&amp;rsquo; ie. writing articles and blogging. Maybe I should jump straight to it and give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A related thought &amp;hellip; There are numerous posts on the Internet about people who are making X thousands of dollars N months after launching, or they do a kickstarter project and smash through the funding target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The common thread? They already had an email newsletter of 3000 readers, or they had 10000 twitter followers, or they were already a well-known member of an existing forum, or something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if I want to solve distribution, I&amp;rsquo;m gonna need something like that. I need people who are reading what I&amp;rsquo;m writing. I need to interact with people who I can bounce ideas off. I need people who I can reach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright. Fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s give this content-marketing/blogging thing a try. Let&amp;rsquo;s learn more about &amp;lsquo;marketing stuff&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let&amp;rsquo;s not just read about it. Let&amp;rsquo;s do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;m gonna write a blog, get some practical experience at content marketing, and see how things go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either it&amp;rsquo;s going to work: The next time I launch a new project, it will be more likely to succeed as I&amp;rsquo;ll be better at distribution (hopefully).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or it&amp;rsquo;s not going to work: I should stop building things and concentrate on paid work instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;* * *&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;m gonna write a blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let&amp;rsquo;s refine the idea a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t want to do something where I&amp;rsquo;m blatantly blogging just to monetise or to push a sale. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to be a shill for my next project (whatever that might be). It&amp;rsquo;s not all just about money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to write about stuff I&amp;rsquo;m interested in (Software, technology, startups, life, etc.). Otherwise it&amp;rsquo;ll turn in a drag and I&amp;rsquo;ll lose motivation. There has to be some intrinsic value in it too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having opened my mind to the idea of blogging, I&amp;rsquo;ve suddenly had a lot of ideas for things to write about. Things that my subconscious has always wanted to talk about but never got the chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m excited. Yes, it&amp;rsquo;s new and very different from building things, but it sounds like it could be fun too. (I&amp;rsquo;m also a little nervous) Hopefully, it also turns out well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent most of nine months writing Gig&amp;rsquo;o&amp;rsquo;Books. Imagine if I spent nine months blogging. I wonder what the results would be? Only one way to find out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here I am. A new beginning. Let&amp;rsquo;s do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wish me luck!&lt;/p&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
