<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>privacy on Beng Tan</title>
    <link>https://bengtan.com/tags/privacy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in privacy on Beng Tan</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-au</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 12:00:00 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://bengtan.com/tags/privacy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>email-untracker: Get rid of tracking links and spy pixels (self-hosted)</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/blog/email-untracker/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 12:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/blog/email-untracker/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;Following up on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://bengtan.com/blog/untracker-remove-tracking-from-email/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;d like to announce that email-untracker (or Untracker for short) is now available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can now run Untracker (on your own self-hosted mail server) for yourself and your friends. Get rid of tracking links and pixels in email newsletters without compromising your own privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or if you&amp;rsquo;re just curious, you can also use Untracker to scan individual emails and see what it discovers. This can be done on your computer and doesn&amp;rsquo;t require a mail server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TL;DR: Go straight to the Github &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bengtan/email-untracker&#34;&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-info&#34;&gt;More info&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Untracker is a sponsorware project hosted at Github. The public repository is &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bengtan/email-untracker&#34;&gt;https://github.com/bengtan/email-untracker&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, the binaries are &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bengtan/email-untracker/releases&#34;&gt;publicly available&lt;/a&gt; but the source code is in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bengtan/email-untracker-sponsorware/&#34;&gt;sponsors-only repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once 75 sponsors have been reached, I&amp;rsquo;ll open source it and publish the code to the public repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Why did I choose 75? I dunno, I just copied &lt;a href=&#34;https://calebporzio.com/sponsorware&#34;&gt;https://calebporzio.com/sponsorware&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that (and if the number of sponsors remains 75 or more), I will semi-regularly publish code from the sponsors-only repository to the public repository. (The sponsors-only repository will always have the latest code and newest features.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a small change in licensing from what I originally proposed. The sponsors-only repository is licensed under a &amp;lsquo;source available&amp;rsquo; license to discourage redistribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading, and I hope you find Untracker useful!&lt;/p&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Untracker: Uncloak tracking links and remove spy pixels from email newsletters</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/blog/untracker-remove-tracking-from-email/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Mar 2021 12:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/blog/untracker-remove-tracking-from-email/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;h2 id=&#34;previously&#34;&gt;Previously&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I wrote Email Cleaner and started using it to clean tracking links and pixels from my email newsletters. It works well. I can hover over links (or long press for touch devices) and see the URL. I can click on them &lt;strong&gt;without being tracked&lt;/strong&gt;. I can protect myself from phishing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I &lt;a href=&#34;https://bengtan.com/blog/email-cleaner-clean-tracking-links-and-pixels/&#34;&gt;announced Email Cleaner&lt;/a&gt; to the world, I got &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=26293424&#34;&gt;some feedback&lt;/a&gt; from the great people at Hacker News. (I also posted to a couple of other places but didn&amp;rsquo;t get any comments.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two things stood out in the feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; you get my Email address and newsletters I like. &amp;hellip; Now it is a question of trusting a random guy on the internet to be better and not sell my data to the highest bidder. Maybe open source could address this to some extend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=26313017&#34;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=26313017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were privacy concerns. Some didn&amp;rsquo;t like the idea of sending their email newsletters to a third party. Fair enough, I understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;this [is] something that should be directly integrated into email clients, not something I would get a third party app for&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=26300617&#34;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=26300617&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was suggested that a service such as Email Cleaner should be integrated into the email client. I agree and disagree. It naturally belongs in the email system though not necessarily at the client side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I&amp;rsquo;m probably biased. Working with email clients is like fighting a multi-headed hydra. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to go there. 😊)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came up with a new approach to address these concerns. I could rewrite Email Cleaner to be self-hosted, open source, and plug into mail servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be like &amp;lsquo;Email Cleaner v2&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I still want to monetise it somehow. (I know this can be controversial. Read more about it below.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;d like to talk about this and see what you, the readers and potential users, think. It will help me guage whether this is viable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you disagree with me, the discussion below about monetising open source is still interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;proposal&#34;&gt;Proposal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is Email Cleaner v2?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, I&amp;rsquo;m going to change the name to Untracker. Emphasising the anti-tracking aspect seems to connect with users better. It&amp;rsquo;s still the same functionality as before but with different packaging and branding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(From here on, Email Cleaner refers to the original SaaS service. Untracker refers to this new &amp;lsquo;v2&amp;rsquo; proposal.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Untracker will be an &lt;strong&gt;open source&lt;/strong&gt; utility that can be plugged into &lt;strong&gt;self-hosted&lt;/strong&gt; email servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Untracker sits in front of an email mailbox (like a Mail Delivery Agent). When it receives an email, it processes the email by cleaning tracking links and pixels. (For an explanation of what cleaning involves, &lt;a href=&#34;https://bengtan.com/blog/email-cleaner-clean-tracking-links-and-pixels/&#34;&gt;please see the previous article&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, depending on configuration, it can:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Send the cleaned email back to the sender, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Send the cleaned email to a preconfigured email address, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deliver the cleaned email to the mailbox.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first mode is how Email Cleaner currently works. Send an email newsletter to it and it will reply with the cleaned version. This mode uses a dedicated email address to reach the service. (For example, Email Cleaner uses &lt;code&gt;email-cleaner@bengtan.com&lt;/code&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second mode is a minor variation of the first. It sends to a preconfigured email address instead. This mode uses an intermediate email address (ie. &lt;code&gt;subscriptions@domain&lt;/code&gt;) which can act as a man-in-the-middle email forwarder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third mode delivers the cleaned email to the user&amp;rsquo;s inbox. Each email newsletter appears in the inbox twice: The original version and the cleaned version. This mode does not require an additional email address. It is the most exciting because it integrates closely with the email system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever the mode of operation, the emails stay on the server. They are not sent to a third party (ie. me).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Untracker requires that you self-host your own email server. If you&amp;rsquo;re not self-hosting, maybe you can find a friend who is. Your friend can configure Untracker in mode 1 or 2 and you can send your newsletters to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can&amp;rsquo;t find anyone to run Untracker for you, you can use the original Email Cleaner service (but you&amp;rsquo;d be sending your email newsletters to a third party ie. me).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;monetisation&#34;&gt;Monetisation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self-hosted Untracker will be open source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;ve already mentioned above that I want to monetise it somehow. This is important to me. I&amp;rsquo;m trying to &lt;a href=&#34;https://onlysponsors.dev/&#34;&gt;build a salary&lt;/a&gt; for myself so I can work full-time on open source or other projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem-with-github-sponsors&#34;&gt;The problem with Github Sponsors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sponsors&#34;&gt;Github Sponsors&lt;/a&gt; looks like the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there is a problem with Github Sponsors. It&amp;rsquo;s the same problem whenever payments are optional. The problem is human nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In theory, sponsorship (or synonymously, &amp;lsquo;donationware&amp;rsquo;) sounds great. In practice, the &amp;lsquo;conversion&amp;rsquo; rate is too low. I don&amp;rsquo;t have any hard metrics but I vaguely remember reading articles years ago. They cite the rate of donations to be some crazy low number like 0.001% or something. It&amp;rsquo;s just too low to be practical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FWIW, I&amp;rsquo;ve also tried donationware in the past, and my experience corroborates with this. People just don&amp;rsquo;t donate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t blame people. If you&amp;rsquo;re not pushed to pay money for something, you usually don&amp;rsquo;t think about it. It&amp;rsquo;s just the way it is. &lt;strong&gt;Donationware doesn&amp;rsquo;t work unless it&amp;rsquo;s pushed in-your-face&lt;/strong&gt;. Massively in-your-face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see similar characteristics with Github Sponsors. When I look at developers who offer sponsorship, I often see unsustainably low sponsorship rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there is an outlier: The &lt;a href=&#34;https://calebporzio.com/i-just-hit-dollar-100000yr-on-github-sponsors-heres-how-i-did-it&#34;&gt;high profile case&lt;/a&gt; of Caleb Porzio, a developer who has &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sponsors/calebporzio&#34;&gt;1370+ sponsors and $20k+/month&lt;/a&gt; (estimated) in sponsorships (and is still growing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;calebporzio-sponsors.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;screenshot: calebporzio&amp;rsquo;s sponsors&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compare this against a core developer of one of the most widely used javascript frameworks. This second developer has the &amp;lsquo;normal&amp;rsquo; low rate of sponsors. He has &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sponsors/posva&#34;&gt;73 sponsors and $2k/month&lt;/a&gt; in sponsorships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;posva-sponsors.png&#34; alt=&#34;screenshot: posva&amp;rsquo;s sponsors&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s a massive difference between Caleb and the second developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What accounts for the difference? Caleb has less github followers (2.6k vs 2.7k), more twitter followers (23.3k vs 10.8k) and a higher minimum sponsorship tier ($14 vs $1). These aren&amp;rsquo;t the reason. For example, they don&amp;rsquo;t explain the disparity in number of sponsors (1370 vs 73).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;payment-decision-point&#34;&gt;Payment Decision Point&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the reason is hiding in plain sight: Caleb charges for value added content. He says so himself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sponsored Screencasts &amp;hellip; This is where the VAST majority of my sponsorships came from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few weeks later I added a new “private” group of screencasts for GitHub sponsors only. &amp;hellip; THIS is the secret sauce 🌶️.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://calebporzio.com/i-just-hit-dollar-100000yr-on-github-sponsors-heres-how-i-did-it&#34;&gt;https://calebporzio.com/i-just-hit-dollar-100000yr-on-github-sponsors-heres-how-i-did-it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His sponsorships aren&amp;rsquo;t really sponsorships in the usual sense of the word. Instead, they are payments for premium content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This comes back to what I said above. Donationware doesn&amp;rsquo;t work unless it&amp;rsquo;s in-your-face. There is nothing more in-your-face than &amp;lsquo;you have to pay for this&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People are paying Caleb because they want to sponsor him but also because they want content. I suspect the latter is much greater than the former.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s another statistic. During the few days between conceptualising and then writing this article, the number of his sponsors has gone from 1331 to 1370. That&amp;rsquo;s 39 new sponsors in a few days. Wow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t expect such a high rate of new sponsors if it was purely to sponsor him per se. There&amp;rsquo;s something else going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;* * *&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway. This makes me think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I want to make &amp;lsquo;sponsored open source&amp;rsquo; work, there has to be a payment for &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;. And the &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; has to be (somewhat) valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has to be a &amp;lsquo;Payment Decision Point&amp;rsquo; where potential sponsors are forced to confront the question &amp;lsquo;Oh, is this where I make a payment now?&amp;rsquo;. Otherwise people won&amp;rsquo;t think about it. They&amp;rsquo;ll move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To achieve sustainable sponsorship with Untracker, I have to put something behind a paywall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;untrackers-sponsorship-model&#34;&gt;Untracker&amp;rsquo;s sponsorship model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the proposed sponsorship model with an in-built Payment Decision Point. I hope this will allow Untracker to be both open source and monetised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A public repository will contain the compiled binary and entry level documentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The binary will be free for non-commercial use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Source code and advanced documentation will be in a private repository accessible by sponsors only.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The source code will be open source. I&amp;rsquo;ve currently settled on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gnu.org/licenses/agpl-3.0.en.html&#34;&gt;Affero General Public License Version 3&lt;/a&gt; (AGPL) license.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sponsors are encouraged to build from source. Commercial usage is allowed under the open source license.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sponsorship starts at $12 per month. Higher tiers are available for super fans and companies. I&amp;rsquo;ll regularly review the sponsorship tiers for suitability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a freemium model. Most people can use Untracker for free but sponsorship unlocks further benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sponsors get all the usual benefits of open source. They can inspect and modify the source code. They get access to support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They can also redistribute the source code. I hope they don&amp;rsquo;t though I can&amp;rsquo;t enforce it. Redistribution would completely break this model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope sponsors see value in continuing sponsorship. It pays for support, new features (see below) and ongoing maintenance. Maintenance will be required because this is a cat-and-mouse game with the mailing list providers. Once they learn about Untracker, I expect them to change their tracking links to try to avoid it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, I get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To continue to work on Untracker, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One component of my quest to build a salary for myself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this model strikes a good balance for everyone and nurtures both Untracker and the Untracker community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-stuff&#34;&gt;Other stuff&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some other random information. Skip over any uninteresting bits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rewrite&#34;&gt;Rewrite&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Untracker will be a completely new rewrite. The original Email Cleaner code has some hardcoded constants specific to my internal email setup and is unsuitable for publishing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Untracker will be written in golang and compiles to a single CLI binary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;bypassing-tracking-entirely&#34;&gt;Bypassing tracking entirely&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have one really great feature in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally, the destination URL of a tracking link is discovered by crawling it. This triggers a one-off tracking event at the mailing list provider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve since discovered that some mailing list providers encode the destination URL in the link itself. For these cases, Untracker can decode the URL without crawling, thus &lt;strong&gt;bypassing tracking&lt;/strong&gt; entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-features&#34;&gt;Other features&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some other features I&amp;rsquo;d like to add:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert emails to plain text (or rather, just omit the HTML part) — The ultimate in privacy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;lsquo;Deep inspection&amp;rsquo; mode which crawls all links and images and report any which are trackers. Useful for detecting new, unknown trackers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Crawling via a HTTP proxy (or tor!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;one-time-sponsorship-as-a-payment&#34;&gt;One-time sponsorship as a payment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A user could sponsor, download the source code, and then unsponsor. They&amp;rsquo;d be effectively &amp;lsquo;buying&amp;rsquo; the source code for $12. I&amp;rsquo;m fine with this. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to complicate the revenue model just to extract a bit more money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I hope that when they join, they like what they see and decide to stay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-source-not-open-contribution&#34;&gt;Open source, not open contribution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve currently decided not to accept source code patches. This is for a number of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can restrain creeping featurism and keep the code tight, thus reducing long term maintenance burden and potential for burn-out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It avoids any ambiguity over copyright of Untracker. I would like to retain copyright over it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some FLOSS contributors get upset when open source software (which has some community-contributed patches) is monetised or relicensed under a different software license. I don&amp;rsquo;t have an opinion on this argument but I&amp;rsquo;d like to avoid it entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope I don&amp;rsquo;t sound unfriendly about this. I&amp;rsquo;d be happy for the community to get involved and post bug reports and feature requests. These activities are valuable too. Software development isn&amp;rsquo;t just coding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do submit source code patches, I&amp;rsquo;d happily look at them but I&amp;rsquo;d rewrite them from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;alternative-licensing&#34;&gt;Alternative licensing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If any sponsors find the AGPL unsuitable for their use, please contact me and we can work something out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;untracking-regular-email&#34;&gt;Untracking regular email&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In theory, Untracker can untrack all email, not just newsletters. In practice, there might be some weird cases which break. For now, I recommend passing only newsletters through Untracker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expanding Untracker to handle all email is a possible long term goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;original-email-cleaner-service&#34;&gt;Original Email Cleaner service&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will continue to operate the original Email Cleaner service. I still use it myself. Maybe there is demand for a SaaS version of Untracker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point, Email Cleaner will be powered by Untracker code instead of the old code. However, there is no need for existing users to take any action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, here&amp;rsquo;s a big &amp;lsquo;Thank You!&amp;rsquo; to the users of Email Cleaner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They have provided me with new, previously un-represented, test cases. This has resulted in increased coverage of tracking links. The improvements will feed into Untracker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hope&#34;&gt;Hope&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope Untracker succeeds and many people find it useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope the sponsorship model turns out to be a good compromise between the traditional tensions of open source vs monetisation. If it inspires others to attain more funding for open source software, then all the better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also hope my thoughts about Payment Decision Points helps others &amp;lsquo;crack the code&amp;rsquo; and replicate Caleb Porzio&amp;rsquo;s so-far-unreplicated success with sponsorships. Was it insightful? Only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;feedback-and-validation&#34;&gt;Feedback and validation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: I haven&amp;rsquo;t done any of the above. I haven&amp;rsquo;t started Untracker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, Untracker is just a bunch of ideas and an article — A proposal awaiting feedback and validation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope it generates a lot of interest, as that is a sure sign that I should proceed. But I can&amp;rsquo;t be certain. This is why I&amp;rsquo;d like to ask for your feedback. If you have any feedback, comments or questions, I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a long article so here&amp;rsquo;s a refresher of sub-topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you think about the name change to Untracker?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you think about Untracker (as a product)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you think about Untracker being open source but requiring self-hosting?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you think of the discussion about Github Sponsors and the Payment Decision Point?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you think about Untracker&amp;rsquo;s freemium/monetisation/sponsorship model?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be notified of updates about Untracker, please subscribe to my newsletter (You can choose to be notified about Untracker only). I hope that my next article about Untracker will report some positive developments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Email Cleaner: Clean tracking links and pixels from email newsletters</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/blog/email-cleaner-clean-tracking-links-and-pixels/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Feb 2021 12:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/blog/email-cleaner-clean-tracking-links-and-pixels/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(UPDATE @2021-03-12: There is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://bengtan.com/blog/untracker-remove-tracking-from-email/&#34;&gt;follow-up post&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m supposed to be blogging instead of doing &lt;a href=&#34;https://bengtan.com/blog/app-startup-vs-content-startup/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;app startup&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; things but I got sidetracked and built another side project (again).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been getting into email newsletters. Over the last month, I&amp;rsquo;ve gone from zero newsletters to eleven of them. My inbox is now overflowing with newsletters. Maybe I&amp;rsquo;ll have to cut back but that&amp;rsquo;s a story for another time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a new pet hate: Links in email newsletters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are user-hostile. Substack is the worst. Their URLs look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://email.substack.com/c/ejXDKM2OhCAMgJ9muI3hT3QOHPayr2EKVIesgwbquL794njbhEIhNP36eSCclnzYdSnEzm2gY0WbcC8zEmFmW8E8xGBlb1pljGTBdsJpLVksw5gRXxBnS3lDtm5ujh4oLulTIVvJnjbgCKC51hxawbuuxzCCcwHAo0CprrawhYjJo8U35mNJyGb7JFrLTX3d5Hdd-743CWjL2PjlVR8gU_qZLpoGLdre3LkUd87Vw9wrnZX1ymUN3XbtoxENjIYbFKBVq3wrxlF47oLolZNKonrcNC-bKwT-RzT4u1aKRBHmd8S99mTZOkwTQRL153TOfZKcYw_1fG0p0jFgAjdjuIzQJfbjaJgwYa7CwwBkhRGq75Xu-4fpLgVVmZKdFNUzqxxhqVXJ_uP4AyNKkNQ&#34;&gt;http://email.substack.com/c/ejXDKM2OhCAMgJ9muI3hT3QOHPayr2EKVIesgwbquL794njbhEIhNP36eSCclnzYdSnEzm2gY0WbcC8zEmFmW8E8xGBlb1pljGTBdsJpLVksw5gRXxBnS3lDtm5ujh4oLulTIVvJnjbgCKC51hxawbuuxzCCcwHAo0CprrawhYjJo8U35mNJyGb7JFrLTX3d5Hdd-743CWjL2PjlVR8gU_qZLpoGLdre3LkUd87Vw9wrnZX1ymUN3XbtoxENjIYbFKBVq3wrxlF47oLolZNKonrcNC-bKwT-RzT4u1aKRBHmd8S99mTZOkwTQRL153TOfZKcYw_1fG0p0jFgAjdjuIzQJfbjaJgwYa7CwwBkhRGq75Xu-4fpLgVVmZKdFNUzqxxhqVXJ_uP4AyNKkNQ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is that, Substack?! Is that really a URL with 400+ characters?!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have an ingrained habit of hovering over links. This allows me to see where it links to and decide whether to click on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a good habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s also a security &amp;ldquo;best practice&amp;rdquo;. Hovering over a link helps to check whether it&amp;rsquo;s a phishing link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email newsletters have broken this. I have no idea where these user-hostile links go. For their own self interest, mailing list service providers have denied me a basic tenet of the web: Knowing what I&amp;rsquo;m clicking on before I click.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s also demeans the newsletter. A newsletter which purports to send me a &amp;lsquo;list of interesting links&amp;rsquo; is just sending me a list of crap because I&amp;rsquo;m not clicking on those I-have-no-idea-where-it&amp;rsquo;s-going links.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the link was something like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;url=https://www.wikipedia.org/&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw3ay7vaEtH0yTTYdDmrvinX&#34;&gt;http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;url=https://www.wikipedia.org/&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw3ay7vaEtH0yTTYdDmrvinX&lt;/a&gt; I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be as peeved because I can see where it links to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But no, I don&amp;rsquo;t think they&amp;rsquo;ll compromise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I set about trying to make the situation palatable. I asked &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=26188976&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/SomebodyMakeThis/comments/ln4dep/smt_hover_over_links_in_email_newsletters_and_see/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.indiehackers.com/post/17a17962db&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; but I didn&amp;rsquo;t find anything satisfactory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I built my own solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-it&#34;&gt;What is it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hooked a script up to an email address. Upon receiving an email, the script will replace tracking links with their destination URL, remove tracking pixels, and send it back to the sender.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, I set up a gmail filter to forward my newsletters to the script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yay!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, when I receive an email newsletter, gmail forwards it to the script. The script sends it back to me with nice clean URLs. Once again, I can see where links lead to before I decide whether to click.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tracking parameters (ie. &lt;code&gt;utm_*&lt;/code&gt;) and tracking pixels are removed as well. (I don&amp;rsquo;t care strongly about this but it was easy to add so I did.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;email-cleaner&#34;&gt;Email Cleaner&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For lack of a better name, I&amp;rsquo;m calling it &lt;strong&gt;Email Cleaner&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;It cleans crap from email newsletters&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Alternatively, I considered calling it &amp;lsquo;&lt;strong&gt;UntrackMe: Remove tracking from email newsletters&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rsquo;. Which sounds better?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m letting others try it. Maybe other people find it useful too. If there&amp;rsquo;s enough interest, I&amp;rsquo;ll turn it into a proper side project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;getting-started&#34;&gt;Getting started&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To try Email Cleaner, forward an email newsletter to &lt;code&gt;email-cleaner@bengtan.com&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a minute or two, you should get the newsletter sent back to you (from &lt;code&gt;no-reply@bengtan.com&lt;/code&gt;) with cleaned links and tracking pixels removed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you decide you like it, you can set up your email program to automatically forward email newsletters to &lt;code&gt;email-cleaner@bengtan.com&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How you do this depends on your email program so you&amp;rsquo;ll have to work it out youself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Please don&amp;rsquo;t set up your email program to automatically delete after forwarding. Since this is a new service, it&amp;rsquo;s a good idea to retain the original emails in case something goes wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;forwarding-loops&#34;&gt;Forwarding loops&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your automatic forwarding configuration mistakenly forwards the cleaned email (from Email Cleaner) back to Email Cleaner, it will detect this and send you an email with the message &amp;ldquo;Infinite loop detected&amp;rdquo;. If you get such an email, please adjust your forwarding configuration so you don&amp;rsquo;t forward cleaned emails to Email Cleaner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you use gmail (like I do), this can be accomplished by adding the condition &lt;code&gt;-subject:[email-cleaner]&lt;/code&gt; to your forwarding filter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-it-works&#34;&gt;How it works&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email Cleaner works as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It scans the email for links which match the following regular expressions:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34; data-lang=&#34;js&#34;&gt;	&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;\.list-manage\.com/track/click&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,
	&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;//click\.convertkit-mail\.com/&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,
	&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;//email\.substack.*/c/&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,
	&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;//apple\.co/&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,
	&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;//t\.co/&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If a link matches, then it&amp;rsquo;s a tracking link. Email Cleaner crawls the link to see if it&amp;rsquo;s a 3xx redirect. If it is, then the link is replaced by the destination URL.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any URL query parameters which are &lt;code&gt;mc_cid&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;mc_eid&lt;/code&gt;, or start with &lt;code&gt;utm_&lt;/code&gt; are also removed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then, Email Cleaner scans the email for tracking pixels. If any are found, it removes them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, the email is sent back to the sender.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email Cleaner is quite safe and conservative. It will only crawl links which are obviously tracking links.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email Cleaner currently handles three major mailing list service providers (MailChimp, ConvertKit, Substack). I&amp;rsquo;d happily add more. Just let me know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that Email Cleaner doesn&amp;rsquo;t magically bypass the tracking links. Instead, it triggers all of them from a data centre somewhere. It&amp;rsquo;s privacy-by-obfuscation instead of privacy-by-abstention. But it does prevent your web browser/IP address/location from being leaked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;benefits&#34;&gt;Benefits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Email newsletters are more user friendly. (I&amp;rsquo;m more inclined to click on a link if I see it&amp;rsquo;s a reputable website.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Helps detect phishing attacks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better user privacy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plain text emails are readable again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;plain-text-emails&#34;&gt;Plain text emails&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last benefit was an unexpected side effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whilst writing Email Cleaner, I discovered that plain text versions of email newsletters are completely unreadable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most agree that the term Artificial Intelligence was codified at a Dartmouth workshop in 1956 [httр://email.substack.com/c/eJxdkc-OgyAQh5-m3Grkr3rgsJd9DQM4WlIFA2O7vv1O2-xlE2CSHzPhy0dwCEsup91zRfY6Rjx3sAmegAiF7BsUE71mvZJcKUa87qgTgpG4mVAAXjYuGssOZN3dEkeLMafPBpOMzFp1wluppHM9Z2FoQQQbnAqd8tx2A7_P2t1HSCNoeEM5cwKy6Blx3R7868F-qkFqjviMK_hom1ym2rrqmr5twVfecTZHLs9tziuJmrWMtqy6kJ0cGtrYoFoF1Aou-ShpCHRsnac9d4wz4MNDtNvuNrTjkzbwu1YNCaNd3hGOZsykaAdpQptonZyur2v3dT1tan7tKeJpIFm3gL954I31Q8hMkKBU3N5Y1FRR3vdc9P2guhtABcZZx2ilTKoOn-tW0v90_AEVdJLl]. At a conference five years earlier [httр://email.substack.com/c/eJxdkEtuhDAMhk8zWSLyBBZZVKp6jSghDkTDJCiYody-YdhV8kO2bPn3N1qEKZdTr3lDcgWD5wo6wbEtdQVEKOyoUMY4WdEbLY0RbLId90oJFus4F4DNxdViOYDth19jcBhzek8ILdjNDk5xrQxozWenoTNmkL2cvQoimFaZz7PumCKkABYeUM6cgK32hrjXi_y6iG9aIW_7QUS3WJGQm1wWSv2aXwVvMd1jWq7O5wOvmwsUQL26NF3_7qiNRStawVtBW-lODw1v3GxaA9wpqWUgxpmH1k-8l15IAXK4qLYevqILd97Az05sCaNbHxGeTcisWA9pQZc4dS4vG5RuLxkj1e1IEc8RkvMrTB9P-NH9NjcukKDQN0yjQ8sNl30vVd8PpvuIIZFSdIKTfUYcU6apZP9x_AIL9Jrk], however, the concepts were discussed in detail, just not named. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is that supposed to be readable?! (It&amp;rsquo;s not just Substack. The other providers are almost just as bad.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email Cleaner changes it to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most agree that the term Artificial Intelligence was codified at a Dartmouth workshop in 1956 [httрs://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dartmouth_workshop]. At a conference five years earlier [httрs://computerhistory.org/blog/thinking-about-machines-and-thinking/], however, the concepts were discussed in detail, just not named. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which is moderately readable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be even better if it was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most agree that the term Artificial Intelligence was codified at a Dartmouth workshop in 1956 [0]. At a conference five years earlier [1], however, the concepts were discussed in detail, just not named. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[0] httрs://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dartmouth_workshop&lt;br /&gt;
[1] httрs://computerhistory.org/blog/thinking-about-machines-and-thinking/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;but that&amp;rsquo;s a story for another time. (I don&amp;rsquo;t know if it&amp;rsquo;s worth the effort to do this. Do many people still read emails in plain text?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;caveats&#34;&gt;Caveats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please note that Email Cleaner is only a proof of concept. It&amp;rsquo;s an experiment. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t even call it an MVP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s useful to me, but I don&amp;rsquo;t know if it&amp;rsquo;s useful for others. I&amp;rsquo;d like to find out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know how long Email Cleaner will last since:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s vulnerable to spam (There&amp;rsquo;s no authentication or access control), and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not scalable (It&amp;rsquo;s running on a tiny server).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the spam bots arrive, or too many people use it, it&amp;rsquo;ll probably have to stop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or if there&amp;rsquo;s sufficient interest, I&amp;rsquo;ll rewrite it into a proper side project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;privacy&#34;&gt;Privacy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please don&amp;rsquo;t forward any personal or private emails to Email Cleaner. Only forward publicly available email newsletters (Paid newsletters are okay).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All received emails go to Email Cleaner&amp;rsquo;s inbox. I hope to accumulate more test data with which to conduct further research on mailing list service providers and improve Email Cleaner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s not really a privacy policy. This is an experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you forward emails to Email Cleaner, I consider that as your opt-in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anything you forward to Email Cleaner could be used to improve Email Cleaner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OTOH, I don&amp;rsquo;t know anything about you anyway. All I have is an email address and what email newsletters you subscribe to (whatever can be inferred from that).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;feedback&#34;&gt;Feedback&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this is a new and experimental service, please don&amp;rsquo;t expect it to be perfectly reliable nor correct. If you forward an email to Email Cleaner and don&amp;rsquo;t get a reply in a few minutes, maybe something broke. Please get in touch with me and I&amp;rsquo;d be happy to look into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions, suggestions, criticisms, etc. — please also let me know. I&amp;rsquo;d be happy to talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you like Email Cleaner! Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
