<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Personal website of Beng Tan on Beng Tan</title>
    <link>https://bengtan.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Personal website of Beng Tan on Beng Tan</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-au</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://bengtan.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Things #1 — The Adjacent Possible</title>
      <link>https://interestingthings.bengtan.com/p/issue-1</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/links/interesting-things-001/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;Welcome to the very first edition of Interesting Things, a curation of interesting stories and links from tech, indie business, science, and adjacents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are things I came across during my Internet wanderings. I find them interesting, and I hope you do too. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Status update (2021-04-14)</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/blog/status-update-20210414/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2021 09:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/blog/status-update-20210414/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;Sorry, I stopped blogging for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Astute readers will have noticed that I haven&amp;rsquo;t posted any original blog posts for a few weeks. I&amp;rsquo;ve been irregularly posting &lt;a href=&#34;https://bengtan.com/reading-list&#34;&gt;Reading Lists&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reason?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m tinkering with setting up an email newsletter of curated links. I do a lot of reading every week and I think some of the more interesting stories I come across would also be interesting to other people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying out different things and experimenting with different formats. I&amp;rsquo;m not quite happy with it yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, once that&amp;rsquo;s done (in a couple more weeks?), I&amp;rsquo;ll be back to blogging or some other side project. It won&amp;rsquo;t be long!&lt;/p&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>email-untracker: Get rid of tracking links and spy pixels (self-hosted)</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/blog/email-untracker/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 12:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/blog/email-untracker/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;Following up on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://bengtan.com/blog/untracker-remove-tracking-from-email/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;d like to announce that email-untracker (or Untracker for short) is now available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can now run Untracker (on your own self-hosted mail server) for yourself and your friends. Get rid of tracking links and pixels in email newsletters without compromising your own privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or if you&amp;rsquo;re just curious, you can also use Untracker to scan individual emails and see what it discovers. This can be done on your computer and doesn&amp;rsquo;t require a mail server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TL;DR: Go straight to the Github &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bengtan/email-untracker&#34;&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-info&#34;&gt;More info&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Untracker is a sponsorware project hosted at Github. The public repository is &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bengtan/email-untracker&#34;&gt;https://github.com/bengtan/email-untracker&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, the binaries are &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bengtan/email-untracker/releases&#34;&gt;publicly available&lt;/a&gt; but the source code is in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bengtan/email-untracker-sponsorware/&#34;&gt;sponsors-only repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once 75 sponsors have been reached, I&amp;rsquo;ll open source it and publish the code to the public repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Why did I choose 75? I dunno, I just copied &lt;a href=&#34;https://calebporzio.com/sponsorware&#34;&gt;https://calebporzio.com/sponsorware&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that (and if the number of sponsors remains 75 or more), I will semi-regularly publish code from the sponsors-only repository to the public repository. (The sponsors-only repository will always have the latest code and newest features.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a small change in licensing from what I originally proposed. The sponsors-only repository is licensed under a &amp;lsquo;source available&amp;rsquo; license to discourage redistribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading, and I hope you find Untracker useful!&lt;/p&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using a proportional font for markdown</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/blog/proportional-font-markdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Mar 2021 12:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/blog/proportional-font-markdown/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, I switched to using a proportional font for editing markdown text. I&amp;rsquo;ve been using vscode&amp;rsquo;s inbuilt markdown previewer a lot. Continually staring at it&amp;rsquo;s proportionally spaced output probably triggered a flash of inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I figured markdown in a more readable font would be a nicer experience. And since I&amp;rsquo;ve started blogging, I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing a lot of prose in markdown so it makes sense to give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took me a day or two to get used to it. But now, I like it, and I&amp;rsquo;m staying with it. Occasionally, the proportional spacing gets in the way, but overall, it&amp;rsquo;s been a great net positive. I encourage everyone to try it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately for me, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to do this in vscode so it affects markdown files only. You want something like this in your &lt;code&gt;settings.json&lt;/code&gt; file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-json&#34; data-lang=&#34;json&#34;&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;[markdown]&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#960050;background-color:#1e0010&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; {
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;editor.fontFamily&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;#39;Segoe WPC&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;Segoe UI&amp;#39;, system-ui, &amp;#39;Ubuntu&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;Droid Sans&amp;#39;, sans-serif&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;,
    }&lt;span style=&#34;color:#960050;background-color:#1e0010&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;where &lt;code&gt;fontFamily&lt;/code&gt; is a list of fonts. I just copied the &lt;code&gt;fontFamily&lt;/code&gt; value from the inbuilt markdown previewer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that I use a proportional font for markdown only. I think this is a clear proposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still using monospace for other stuff. I think proportional fonts for coding is not so clear cut. If you are interested in it, here&amp;rsquo;s some discussions from the past:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://softwareengineering.stackexchange.com/questions/5473&#34;&gt;Does anyone prefer proportional fonts?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=1056683&#34;&gt;Programming with proportional fonts is great&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20130401074244/http://m-mz.posterous.com/programming-with-proportional&#34;&gt;web archive&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A tour of sponsorware</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/blog/tour-of-sponsorware/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2021 12:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/blog/tour-of-sponsorware/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;Been reading into sponsorware to see how it could be used to fund open source. Here&amp;rsquo;s a bunch of links arranged in a semi-timeline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feb 2020 - &lt;a href=&#34;https://calebporzio.com/sponsorware&#34;&gt;Introducing Sponsorware: How A Small Open Source Package Increased My Salary By $11k in Two Days&lt;/a&gt; - The first post by Caleb Porzio that introduces the term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;17 Feb 2020 - &lt;a href=&#34;https://changelog.com/podcast/381&#34;&gt;The dawn of sponsorware&lt;/a&gt; - Caleb is featured on a podcast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mar 2020 - &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sponsorware/docs&#34;&gt;Sponsorware&lt;/a&gt; repository is created.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;09 May 2020 - &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.schlein.net/why-sponsorware-is-not-the-answer/&#34;&gt;Why Sponsorware is not the answer to monetize open source&lt;/a&gt; - Disagrees with &amp;lsquo;sponsorware as early access&amp;rsquo; but agrees with &amp;lsquo;sponsorware as upselling&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jun 2020 - &lt;a href=&#34;https://calebporzio.com/i-just-hit-dollar-100000yr-on-github-sponsors-heres-how-i-did-it&#34;&gt;I Just Hit $100k/yr On GitHub Sponsors! 🎉❤️ (How I Did It)&lt;/a&gt; [&lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=23613719&#34;&gt;Hacker News comments&lt;/a&gt;] - The post that really ignited this space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following are from the same author:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;13 Oct 2020 - &lt;a href=&#34;https://leoloso.com/posts/rector-new-sponsor-graphql-api-for-wp/&#34;&gt;I got my 1st big sponsor for the GraphQL API for WordPress&lt;/a&gt; - Someone who got a $1400/month sponsor but it&amp;rsquo;s more a freelance gig than sponsorship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;24 Oct 2020 - &lt;a href=&#34;https://leoloso.com/posts/funding-wp-plugin-thru-sponsorware/&#34;&gt;Funding a plugin through sponsorware, how successful is it?&lt;/a&gt; - Not really, unless you have 10k subscribers like Caleb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other articles&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;17 Nov 2020 - &lt;a href=&#34;https://porchetta.industries/2020/11/17/And-Now-For-Something-Completely-Diffrent/&#34;&gt;And now for something completely different&amp;hellip;&lt;/a&gt; - An interesting take on sponsorware from the security sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third-party middleware/services start appearing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;19 Oct 2020 - &lt;a href=&#34;https://gumroad.com/l/gumhub&#34;&gt;GumHub&lt;/a&gt; (posted on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.producthunt.com/posts/gumhub&#34;&gt;Product Hunt&lt;/a&gt;) - Sell access to your GitHub repos with Gumroad. Not sponsorware &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt; but similar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nov 2020 - &lt;a href=&#34;https://onlysponsors.dev/&#34;&gt;Only Sponsors&lt;/a&gt; [&lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25882021&#34;&gt;Hacker News comments&lt;/a&gt;] - Build a Salary with GitHub Sponsors - A middleware/service/community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;02 Jan 2021 - &lt;a href=&#34;https://sponsorware.neutron.so/&#34;&gt;Sponsorware for Github&lt;/a&gt; (posted on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.producthunt.com/posts/sponsorware-for-github&#34;&gt;Product Hunt&lt;/a&gt;) - Another middleware/service. Huh? They have &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sponsors/Neutron-Creative&#34;&gt;0 sponsors&lt;/a&gt;. Their dogfood doesn&amp;rsquo;t work every well then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10 Feb 2021 - &lt;a href=&#34;https://opensheetmusicdisplay.org/2021/02/10/sponsorware-videos-screencasting-plugin/&#34;&gt;Sponsorware Screencasting WP Plugin&lt;/a&gt; - There&amp;rsquo;s even a WordPress plugin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dishonourable mention: &lt;a href=&#34;https://joinsponsorware.com/&#34;&gt;https://joinsponsorware.com/&lt;/a&gt; - Someone else trying to cash in but looks unfinished/abandoned? This is sloppy. Why put up a website that&amp;rsquo;s obviously incomplete and (worse) has inappropriate content?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from Only Sponsors (which also offers a community), these services seem a bit dubious. It looks like they sell an access control service, but access control isn&amp;rsquo;t very hard anyway. What is their value proposition? Probably they are just trying to land grab early.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Github repositories&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/byt3bl33d3r/SponsorMonitor&#34;&gt;byt3bl33d3r/SponsorMonitor&lt;/a&gt; - Monitor Github Sponsors and automatically add/remove them to/from a Github Organization Team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jwright/sponsorware-bot&#34;&gt;jwright/sponsorware-bot&lt;/a&gt; - Automates actions based on activity from your GitHub sponsors. - Unmaintained/Unfinished?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/grey-software/sponsorware&#34;&gt;grey-software/Sponsorware&lt;/a&gt; -  Technical guidance and tooling to allow open source developers to distribute software to their Github Sponsors.  - Looks like it&amp;rsquo;s just documentation only?
Related: &lt;a href=&#34;https://gitmemory.com/issue/grey-software/sponsorware/1/689595158&#34;&gt;https://gitmemory.com/issue/grey-software/sponsorware/1/689595158&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/maticzav/sponsorsme&#34;&gt;maticzav/sponsorsme&lt;/a&gt; - A lightweight utility to check whether a user sponsors you.&lt;/p&gt;
        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Untracker: Uncloak tracking links and remove spy pixels from email newsletters</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/blog/untracker-remove-tracking-from-email/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Mar 2021 12:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/blog/untracker-remove-tracking-from-email/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;h2 id=&#34;previously&#34;&gt;Previously&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I wrote Email Cleaner and started using it to clean tracking links and pixels from my email newsletters. It works well. I can hover over links (or long press for touch devices) and see the URL. I can click on them &lt;strong&gt;without being tracked&lt;/strong&gt;. I can protect myself from phishing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I &lt;a href=&#34;https://bengtan.com/blog/email-cleaner-clean-tracking-links-and-pixels/&#34;&gt;announced Email Cleaner&lt;/a&gt; to the world, I got &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=26293424&#34;&gt;some feedback&lt;/a&gt; from the great people at Hacker News. (I also posted to a couple of other places but didn&amp;rsquo;t get any comments.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two things stood out in the feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; you get my Email address and newsletters I like. &amp;hellip; Now it is a question of trusting a random guy on the internet to be better and not sell my data to the highest bidder. Maybe open source could address this to some extend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=26313017&#34;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=26313017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were privacy concerns. Some didn&amp;rsquo;t like the idea of sending their email newsletters to a third party. Fair enough, I understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;this [is] something that should be directly integrated into email clients, not something I would get a third party app for&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=26300617&#34;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=26300617&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was suggested that a service such as Email Cleaner should be integrated into the email client. I agree and disagree. It naturally belongs in the email system though not necessarily at the client side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I&amp;rsquo;m probably biased. Working with email clients is like fighting a multi-headed hydra. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to go there. 😊)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came up with a new approach to address these concerns. I could rewrite Email Cleaner to be self-hosted, open source, and plug into mail servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be like &amp;lsquo;Email Cleaner v2&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I still want to monetise it somehow. (I know this can be controversial. Read more about it below.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;d like to talk about this and see what you, the readers and potential users, think. It will help me guage whether this is viable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you disagree with me, the discussion below about monetising open source is still interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;proposal&#34;&gt;Proposal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is Email Cleaner v2?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, I&amp;rsquo;m going to change the name to Untracker. Emphasising the anti-tracking aspect seems to connect with users better. It&amp;rsquo;s still the same functionality as before but with different packaging and branding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(From here on, Email Cleaner refers to the original SaaS service. Untracker refers to this new &amp;lsquo;v2&amp;rsquo; proposal.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Untracker will be an &lt;strong&gt;open source&lt;/strong&gt; utility that can be plugged into &lt;strong&gt;self-hosted&lt;/strong&gt; email servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Untracker sits in front of an email mailbox (like a Mail Delivery Agent). When it receives an email, it processes the email by cleaning tracking links and pixels. (For an explanation of what cleaning involves, &lt;a href=&#34;https://bengtan.com/blog/email-cleaner-clean-tracking-links-and-pixels/&#34;&gt;please see the previous article&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, depending on configuration, it can:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Send the cleaned email back to the sender, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Send the cleaned email to a preconfigured email address, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deliver the cleaned email to the mailbox.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first mode is how Email Cleaner currently works. Send an email newsletter to it and it will reply with the cleaned version. This mode uses a dedicated email address to reach the service. (For example, Email Cleaner uses &lt;code&gt;email-cleaner@bengtan.com&lt;/code&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second mode is a minor variation of the first. It sends to a preconfigured email address instead. This mode uses an intermediate email address (ie. &lt;code&gt;subscriptions@domain&lt;/code&gt;) which can act as a man-in-the-middle email forwarder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third mode delivers the cleaned email to the user&amp;rsquo;s inbox. Each email newsletter appears in the inbox twice: The original version and the cleaned version. This mode does not require an additional email address. It is the most exciting because it integrates closely with the email system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever the mode of operation, the emails stay on the server. They are not sent to a third party (ie. me).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Untracker requires that you self-host your own email server. If you&amp;rsquo;re not self-hosting, maybe you can find a friend who is. Your friend can configure Untracker in mode 1 or 2 and you can send your newsletters to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can&amp;rsquo;t find anyone to run Untracker for you, you can use the original Email Cleaner service (but you&amp;rsquo;d be sending your email newsletters to a third party ie. me).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;monetisation&#34;&gt;Monetisation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self-hosted Untracker will be open source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;ve already mentioned above that I want to monetise it somehow. This is important to me. I&amp;rsquo;m trying to &lt;a href=&#34;https://onlysponsors.dev/&#34;&gt;build a salary&lt;/a&gt; for myself so I can work full-time on open source or other projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem-with-github-sponsors&#34;&gt;The problem with Github Sponsors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sponsors&#34;&gt;Github Sponsors&lt;/a&gt; looks like the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there is a problem with Github Sponsors. It&amp;rsquo;s the same problem whenever payments are optional. The problem is human nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In theory, sponsorship (or synonymously, &amp;lsquo;donationware&amp;rsquo;) sounds great. In practice, the &amp;lsquo;conversion&amp;rsquo; rate is too low. I don&amp;rsquo;t have any hard metrics but I vaguely remember reading articles years ago. They cite the rate of donations to be some crazy low number like 0.001% or something. It&amp;rsquo;s just too low to be practical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FWIW, I&amp;rsquo;ve also tried donationware in the past, and my experience corroborates with this. People just don&amp;rsquo;t donate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t blame people. If you&amp;rsquo;re not pushed to pay money for something, you usually don&amp;rsquo;t think about it. It&amp;rsquo;s just the way it is. &lt;strong&gt;Donationware doesn&amp;rsquo;t work unless it&amp;rsquo;s pushed in-your-face&lt;/strong&gt;. Massively in-your-face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see similar characteristics with Github Sponsors. When I look at developers who offer sponsorship, I often see unsustainably low sponsorship rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there is an outlier: The &lt;a href=&#34;https://calebporzio.com/i-just-hit-dollar-100000yr-on-github-sponsors-heres-how-i-did-it&#34;&gt;high profile case&lt;/a&gt; of Caleb Porzio, a developer who has &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sponsors/calebporzio&#34;&gt;1370+ sponsors and $20k+/month&lt;/a&gt; (estimated) in sponsorships (and is still growing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;calebporzio-sponsors.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;screenshot: calebporzio&amp;rsquo;s sponsors&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compare this against a core developer of one of the most widely used javascript frameworks. This second developer has the &amp;lsquo;normal&amp;rsquo; low rate of sponsors. He has &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sponsors/posva&#34;&gt;73 sponsors and $2k/month&lt;/a&gt; in sponsorships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;posva-sponsors.png&#34; alt=&#34;screenshot: posva&amp;rsquo;s sponsors&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s a massive difference between Caleb and the second developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What accounts for the difference? Caleb has less github followers (2.6k vs 2.7k), more twitter followers (23.3k vs 10.8k) and a higher minimum sponsorship tier ($14 vs $1). These aren&amp;rsquo;t the reason. For example, they don&amp;rsquo;t explain the disparity in number of sponsors (1370 vs 73).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;payment-decision-point&#34;&gt;Payment Decision Point&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the reason is hiding in plain sight: Caleb charges for value added content. He says so himself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sponsored Screencasts &amp;hellip; This is where the VAST majority of my sponsorships came from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few weeks later I added a new “private” group of screencasts for GitHub sponsors only. &amp;hellip; THIS is the secret sauce 🌶️.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://calebporzio.com/i-just-hit-dollar-100000yr-on-github-sponsors-heres-how-i-did-it&#34;&gt;https://calebporzio.com/i-just-hit-dollar-100000yr-on-github-sponsors-heres-how-i-did-it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His sponsorships aren&amp;rsquo;t really sponsorships in the usual sense of the word. Instead, they are payments for premium content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This comes back to what I said above. Donationware doesn&amp;rsquo;t work unless it&amp;rsquo;s in-your-face. There is nothing more in-your-face than &amp;lsquo;you have to pay for this&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People are paying Caleb because they want to sponsor him but also because they want content. I suspect the latter is much greater than the former.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s another statistic. During the few days between conceptualising and then writing this article, the number of his sponsors has gone from 1331 to 1370. That&amp;rsquo;s 39 new sponsors in a few days. Wow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t expect such a high rate of new sponsors if it was purely to sponsor him per se. There&amp;rsquo;s something else going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;* * *&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway. This makes me think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I want to make &amp;lsquo;sponsored open source&amp;rsquo; work, there has to be a payment for &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;. And the &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; has to be (somewhat) valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has to be a &amp;lsquo;Payment Decision Point&amp;rsquo; where potential sponsors are forced to confront the question &amp;lsquo;Oh, is this where I make a payment now?&amp;rsquo;. Otherwise people won&amp;rsquo;t think about it. They&amp;rsquo;ll move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To achieve sustainable sponsorship with Untracker, I have to put something behind a paywall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;untrackers-sponsorship-model&#34;&gt;Untracker&amp;rsquo;s sponsorship model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the proposed sponsorship model with an in-built Payment Decision Point. I hope this will allow Untracker to be both open source and monetised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A public repository will contain the compiled binary and entry level documentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The binary will be free for non-commercial use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Source code and advanced documentation will be in a private repository accessible by sponsors only.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The source code will be open source. I&amp;rsquo;ve currently settled on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gnu.org/licenses/agpl-3.0.en.html&#34;&gt;Affero General Public License Version 3&lt;/a&gt; (AGPL) license.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sponsors are encouraged to build from source. Commercial usage is allowed under the open source license.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sponsorship starts at $12 per month. Higher tiers are available for super fans and companies. I&amp;rsquo;ll regularly review the sponsorship tiers for suitability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a freemium model. Most people can use Untracker for free but sponsorship unlocks further benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sponsors get all the usual benefits of open source. They can inspect and modify the source code. They get access to support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They can also redistribute the source code. I hope they don&amp;rsquo;t though I can&amp;rsquo;t enforce it. Redistribution would completely break this model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope sponsors see value in continuing sponsorship. It pays for support, new features (see below) and ongoing maintenance. Maintenance will be required because this is a cat-and-mouse game with the mailing list providers. Once they learn about Untracker, I expect them to change their tracking links to try to avoid it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, I get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To continue to work on Untracker, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One component of my quest to build a salary for myself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this model strikes a good balance for everyone and nurtures both Untracker and the Untracker community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-stuff&#34;&gt;Other stuff&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some other random information. Skip over any uninteresting bits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rewrite&#34;&gt;Rewrite&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Untracker will be a completely new rewrite. The original Email Cleaner code has some hardcoded constants specific to my internal email setup and is unsuitable for publishing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Untracker will be written in golang and compiles to a single CLI binary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;bypassing-tracking-entirely&#34;&gt;Bypassing tracking entirely&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have one really great feature in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally, the destination URL of a tracking link is discovered by crawling it. This triggers a one-off tracking event at the mailing list provider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve since discovered that some mailing list providers encode the destination URL in the link itself. For these cases, Untracker can decode the URL without crawling, thus &lt;strong&gt;bypassing tracking&lt;/strong&gt; entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-features&#34;&gt;Other features&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some other features I&amp;rsquo;d like to add:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert emails to plain text (or rather, just omit the HTML part) — The ultimate in privacy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;lsquo;Deep inspection&amp;rsquo; mode which crawls all links and images and report any which are trackers. Useful for detecting new, unknown trackers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Crawling via a HTTP proxy (or tor!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;one-time-sponsorship-as-a-payment&#34;&gt;One-time sponsorship as a payment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A user could sponsor, download the source code, and then unsponsor. They&amp;rsquo;d be effectively &amp;lsquo;buying&amp;rsquo; the source code for $12. I&amp;rsquo;m fine with this. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to complicate the revenue model just to extract a bit more money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I hope that when they join, they like what they see and decide to stay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-source-not-open-contribution&#34;&gt;Open source, not open contribution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve currently decided not to accept source code patches. This is for a number of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can restrain creeping featurism and keep the code tight, thus reducing long term maintenance burden and potential for burn-out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It avoids any ambiguity over copyright of Untracker. I would like to retain copyright over it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some FLOSS contributors get upset when open source software (which has some community-contributed patches) is monetised or relicensed under a different software license. I don&amp;rsquo;t have an opinion on this argument but I&amp;rsquo;d like to avoid it entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope I don&amp;rsquo;t sound unfriendly about this. I&amp;rsquo;d be happy for the community to get involved and post bug reports and feature requests. These activities are valuable too. Software development isn&amp;rsquo;t just coding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do submit source code patches, I&amp;rsquo;d happily look at them but I&amp;rsquo;d rewrite them from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;alternative-licensing&#34;&gt;Alternative licensing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If any sponsors find the AGPL unsuitable for their use, please contact me and we can work something out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;untracking-regular-email&#34;&gt;Untracking regular email&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In theory, Untracker can untrack all email, not just newsletters. In practice, there might be some weird cases which break. For now, I recommend passing only newsletters through Untracker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expanding Untracker to handle all email is a possible long term goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;original-email-cleaner-service&#34;&gt;Original Email Cleaner service&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will continue to operate the original Email Cleaner service. I still use it myself. Maybe there is demand for a SaaS version of Untracker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point, Email Cleaner will be powered by Untracker code instead of the old code. However, there is no need for existing users to take any action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, here&amp;rsquo;s a big &amp;lsquo;Thank You!&amp;rsquo; to the users of Email Cleaner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They have provided me with new, previously un-represented, test cases. This has resulted in increased coverage of tracking links. The improvements will feed into Untracker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hope&#34;&gt;Hope&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope Untracker succeeds and many people find it useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope the sponsorship model turns out to be a good compromise between the traditional tensions of open source vs monetisation. If it inspires others to attain more funding for open source software, then all the better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also hope my thoughts about Payment Decision Points helps others &amp;lsquo;crack the code&amp;rsquo; and replicate Caleb Porzio&amp;rsquo;s so-far-unreplicated success with sponsorships. Was it insightful? Only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;feedback-and-validation&#34;&gt;Feedback and validation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: I haven&amp;rsquo;t done any of the above. I haven&amp;rsquo;t started Untracker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, Untracker is just a bunch of ideas and an article — A proposal awaiting feedback and validation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope it generates a lot of interest, as that is a sure sign that I should proceed. But I can&amp;rsquo;t be certain. This is why I&amp;rsquo;d like to ask for your feedback. If you have any feedback, comments or questions, I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a long article so here&amp;rsquo;s a refresher of sub-topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you think about the name change to Untracker?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you think about Untracker (as a product)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you think about Untracker being open source but requiring self-hosting?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you think of the discussion about Github Sponsors and the Payment Decision Point?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you think about Untracker&amp;rsquo;s freemium/monetisation/sponsorship model?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be notified of updates about Untracker, please subscribe to my newsletter (You can choose to be notified about Untracker only). I hope that my next article about Untracker will report some positive developments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Twitter&#39;s Super Follows could be transformative</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/blog/twitter-super-follows-transformative/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2021 12:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/blog/twitter-super-follows-transformative/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;Twitter&amp;rsquo;s newly announced Super Follows feature could be transformative for the company. I don&amp;rsquo;t just mean &amp;lsquo;It is a good idea&amp;rsquo;. I mean that, in 5+ years time, Twitter could be a completely different company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why? Because Super Follows aligns the incentives for all three parties into a virtuous cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;virtuous-cycle&#34;&gt;Virtuous cycle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virtuous_circle_and_vicious_circle&#34;&gt;virtuous cycle&lt;/a&gt; is a chain of events that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;reinforce themselves through a feedback loop. &amp;hellip; Each iteration of the cycle reinforces the previous one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A virtuous cycle tends to repeat. If it iterates a bit larger or faster each time, this can lead to exponential growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is Amazon&amp;rsquo;s virtuous cycle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;cycle1.svg&#34; alt=&#34;Amazon&amp;rsquo;s virtuous cycle&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look how big it&amp;rsquo;s grown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;adversarial&#34;&gt;Adversarial&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter&amp;rsquo;s main revenue source is advertising. But advertising is adversarial (Both words even come from the same Latin word &lt;em&gt;advertere&lt;/em&gt;). It requires parties playing off against each other:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Users don&amp;rsquo;t want to look at ads. But advertisers want them to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Twitter doesn&amp;rsquo;t really want to show ads. But the need for revenue forces them to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advertisers want attention. But users don&amp;rsquo;t like playing ball.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Growing advertising-based revenue involves a lot of friction and balancing competing interests. Diminishing returns easily sets in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To increase revenue, show more ads. But more ads degrades the user experience and users turn off. Revenue growth slows. To compensate, show more ads. More users turn off. Repeat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a more insidious effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter is incentivised to optimise user engagement. More user engagement means more ad views. More ad views means more revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does Twitter optimise user engagement? One effective way is through anger or outrage. When people are angry, they are motivated to engage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is warped and perverse. Twitter is not just connecting users to people and ideas that matter, but also exposing them to addiction and abuse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the short term, this feels great. Users are engaged. Ad views are up. Revenue is up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the long term, it&amp;rsquo;s a problem. Not just for users&#39; mental health, but for Twitter as well. Optimising for outrage presents a headwind on further growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;substack&#34;&gt;Substack&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Substack gets the virtuous cycle right:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only way we succeed is if writers using Substack succeed &amp;hellip; and writers only succeed if their readers are happy. Everyone’s incentives are aligned&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://on.substack.com/p/the-future-of-substack&#34;&gt;https://on.substack.com/p/the-future-of-substack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beauty here is our growth incentives line up too. As more people choose to pay writers directly, more writers join, and yet more readers follow. Together, we are building new, positive communities of publishers and subscribers, and the whole thing keeps getting better for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://on.substack.com/p/a-new-game&#34;&gt;https://on.substack.com/p/a-new-game&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;super-opportunity&#34;&gt;Super opportunity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Super Follows (in the way it has been described by Twitter so far) is a virtuous cycle. Super Followers pay Creators for content. Creators produce more content. More Super Followers join. Creators are paid more and produce more. Repeat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creators, Super Followers, and Twitter grow together in a virtuous cycle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;cycle2.svg&#34; alt=&#34;Super Followers virtuous cycle&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Super Follows is an opportunity to supplant an adversarial revenue model with one where every one is aligned in the same direction. If Creators succeed, then Super Followers are happy. If Super Followers are happy, then Twitter succeeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A virtuous-cycle-based revenue model has more upside and lifts the ceiling on growth potential. There is much less friction and revenue &amp;lsquo;grows by default&amp;rsquo;. No counter-balancing of competing interests. No diminishing returns. Just let the cycle keep spinning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once Super Follows revenue becomes significant, it will lessen reliance on advertising revenue. Then Twitter can focus on growing the relationships between Creators and Super Followers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key performance metric will no longer be engagement. Engagement becomes just another intermediate step (and relegated to the background). The key performance metric will become number of Super Followers — A holistic metric which has a direct and clearer relationship to revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Super Follows revenue grows enough to dominate advertising revenue, then the &amp;lsquo;feel&amp;rsquo; of Twitter will shift too. It no longer needs to generate anger and outrage. Instead, it will be rewarded for nurturing deeper connections between Creators and their fans. Years later, the experience of using Twitter will be completely different. And better for users&#39; mental health too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we imagine how the the last sentence of the Substack quote might apply to Twitter, it could read: &amp;lsquo;Together, we are building new, positive communities of creators and followers, and the whole thing keeps getting better for everyone.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the future that Super Follows enables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-wildcard-is-apple&#34;&gt;The wildcard is Apple&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I qualify the above with some conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is execution risk. Twitter does not always has a track record of delivering its promises in a timely manner. But we all know that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second risk is the fee breakdown. I presume that Twitter will siphon off some percentage of the payments from the Super Followers to the Creators. Getting the commission rate correct is critical. Too much, and negative publicity about Twitter&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;greed&amp;rsquo; will hold back adoption. Too little, and Twitter can&amp;rsquo;t wean itself off advertising revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Timing is important too. Will Twitter be patient and allow enough time for Super Follows revenue to become significant? Or will it quickly get cold feet and prefer the comfort zone of advertising revenue?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wildcard risk is Apple. Apple&amp;rsquo;s going to want it&amp;rsquo;s 30% cut. 30% of what, though? If a Super Follower pays $10 and Twitter charges 10%, then does Apple want $3 or $0.30? Or can Twitter avoid the Apple tax somehow? This is the most critical risk. It could completely break Super Follows.&lt;/p&gt;
        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on: The Web’s Missing Interoperability</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/blog/the-webs-missing-interoperability/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Mar 2021 12:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/blog/the-webs-missing-interoperability/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;I was reading &lt;a href=&#34;https://stratechery.com/2021/the-webs-missing-interoperability/&#34;&gt;The Web’s Missing Interoperability&lt;/a&gt; from Stratechery (I&amp;rsquo;m an occasional reader) and, for some reason, it really resonated with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took some notes (and made comments) for my own future reference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Web 2.0…refers to websites that emphasize user-generated content, ease of use, participatory culture and interoperability&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That, though, points to Web 2.0’s failure: interoperability is nowhere to be found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bit of misdirection. Missing interoperability is a recurring subtheme but web 2.0 is never mentioned again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the idea of Twitter users being able to charge followers for special access makes all kinds of sense for Twitter the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter&amp;rsquo;s Super Follows could be transformative. Why? Because it aligns the business model (cf Substack, games).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(There&amp;rsquo;s a story here. Maybe even bigger than this one.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the most compelling apps for user-generated content tie creation and consumption into a tight loop, bound together with network effects and presented with a feed that neither creators nor consumers want to leave&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the most challenging part of building a subscription business is customer acquisition&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in a world where distribution is free the real cost is user acquisition&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; Twitter is an obvious channel to do so&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter&amp;rsquo;s social graph could be synergistic with Revue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is also why it is so important that Clubhouse incentivizes its users to import their contacts: the startup is bootstrapping a social network off of your phone’s address book,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in stark contrast to Meerkat, which directly imported your Twitter contacts, right up until the date when Twitter cut it off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter had learned its lesson from Instagram, which booted up its social network on top of the Twitter graph; Twitter eventually cut off Instagram in-line image sharing, but by then it was too late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clubhouse aggressively uploads your contacts because it is bootstrapping a social network/graph. It&amp;rsquo;s existential (to achieve network effects before the incumbents close in).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Censorship and Competition&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talks about censorship and then hyper-warp-jumps to &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A better solution is more competition&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; which leaves me disoriented and confused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two paragraphs later:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, that doesn’t help the “competition as an answer to censorship” problem&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, is this what you were talking about? Why didn&amp;rsquo;t you say so earlier instead of confusing me?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we already have evidence about just how powerful it is when a service lets its social graph be exported, and how limiting it is when it doesn’t. To that end, it seems clear to me that the only way to build a direct competitor to any of these services, like Twitter, is to have direct access to the Twitter network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the solution is clear: force existing social networks to open up their social graphs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem, of course, is privacy;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons why GDPR is such a disaster is that it makes it all but impossible for a new social media company to ever be started in Europe&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Privacy is like security. Security is a tradeoff against convenience. Privacy is a tradeoff against X. What is the best word for X?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to see the social networking giant have more competition, not less, and I despair that the outcome of privacy laws like GDPR, or App Store-enforced policies from Apple, will be to damage Facebook on one hand, and destroy all of its long-term competitors on the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benedict Evans has something &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ben-evans.com/benedictevans/2021/1/17/speech-and-publishing&#34;&gt;similar to say&lt;/a&gt; too:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By making it much harder to share user data between different properties, GDPR had a limited effect beyond inconvenience on Google and Facebook, who mostly keep this data inside one company, but made ad targeting across multiple websites harder and so reduced the ad revenue available to newspaper websites. What the competition regulator gives (or tries to), the privacy regulator takes away. Again - beware of unintended consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or is it tangential?&lt;/p&gt;
        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Email Cleaner: Clean tracking links and pixels from email newsletters</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/blog/email-cleaner-clean-tracking-links-and-pixels/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Feb 2021 12:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/blog/email-cleaner-clean-tracking-links-and-pixels/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(UPDATE @2021-03-12: There is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://bengtan.com/blog/untracker-remove-tracking-from-email/&#34;&gt;follow-up post&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m supposed to be blogging instead of doing &lt;a href=&#34;https://bengtan.com/blog/app-startup-vs-content-startup/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;app startup&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; things but I got sidetracked and built another side project (again).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been getting into email newsletters. Over the last month, I&amp;rsquo;ve gone from zero newsletters to eleven of them. My inbox is now overflowing with newsletters. Maybe I&amp;rsquo;ll have to cut back but that&amp;rsquo;s a story for another time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a new pet hate: Links in email newsletters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are user-hostile. Substack is the worst. Their URLs look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://email.substack.com/c/ejXDKM2OhCAMgJ9muI3hT3QOHPayr2EKVIesgwbquL794njbhEIhNP36eSCclnzYdSnEzm2gY0WbcC8zEmFmW8E8xGBlb1pljGTBdsJpLVksw5gRXxBnS3lDtm5ujh4oLulTIVvJnjbgCKC51hxawbuuxzCCcwHAo0CprrawhYjJo8U35mNJyGb7JFrLTX3d5Hdd-743CWjL2PjlVR8gU_qZLpoGLdre3LkUd87Vw9wrnZX1ymUN3XbtoxENjIYbFKBVq3wrxlF47oLolZNKonrcNC-bKwT-RzT4u1aKRBHmd8S99mTZOkwTQRL153TOfZKcYw_1fG0p0jFgAjdjuIzQJfbjaJgwYa7CwwBkhRGq75Xu-4fpLgVVmZKdFNUzqxxhqVXJ_uP4AyNKkNQ&#34;&gt;http://email.substack.com/c/ejXDKM2OhCAMgJ9muI3hT3QOHPayr2EKVIesgwbquL794njbhEIhNP36eSCclnzYdSnEzm2gY0WbcC8zEmFmW8E8xGBlb1pljGTBdsJpLVksw5gRXxBnS3lDtm5ujh4oLulTIVvJnjbgCKC51hxawbuuxzCCcwHAo0CprrawhYjJo8U35mNJyGb7JFrLTX3d5Hdd-743CWjL2PjlVR8gU_qZLpoGLdre3LkUd87Vw9wrnZX1ymUN3XbtoxENjIYbFKBVq3wrxlF47oLolZNKonrcNC-bKwT-RzT4u1aKRBHmd8S99mTZOkwTQRL153TOfZKcYw_1fG0p0jFgAjdjuIzQJfbjaJgwYa7CwwBkhRGq75Xu-4fpLgVVmZKdFNUzqxxhqVXJ_uP4AyNKkNQ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is that, Substack?! Is that really a URL with 400+ characters?!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have an ingrained habit of hovering over links. This allows me to see where it links to and decide whether to click on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a good habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s also a security &amp;ldquo;best practice&amp;rdquo;. Hovering over a link helps to check whether it&amp;rsquo;s a phishing link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email newsletters have broken this. I have no idea where these user-hostile links go. For their own self interest, mailing list service providers have denied me a basic tenet of the web: Knowing what I&amp;rsquo;m clicking on before I click.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s also demeans the newsletter. A newsletter which purports to send me a &amp;lsquo;list of interesting links&amp;rsquo; is just sending me a list of crap because I&amp;rsquo;m not clicking on those I-have-no-idea-where-it&amp;rsquo;s-going links.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the link was something like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;url=https://www.wikipedia.org/&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw3ay7vaEtH0yTTYdDmrvinX&#34;&gt;http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;url=https://www.wikipedia.org/&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw3ay7vaEtH0yTTYdDmrvinX&lt;/a&gt; I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be as peeved because I can see where it links to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But no, I don&amp;rsquo;t think they&amp;rsquo;ll compromise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I set about trying to make the situation palatable. I asked &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=26188976&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/SomebodyMakeThis/comments/ln4dep/smt_hover_over_links_in_email_newsletters_and_see/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.indiehackers.com/post/17a17962db&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; but I didn&amp;rsquo;t find anything satisfactory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I built my own solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-it&#34;&gt;What is it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hooked a script up to an email address. Upon receiving an email, the script will replace tracking links with their destination URL, remove tracking pixels, and send it back to the sender.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, I set up a gmail filter to forward my newsletters to the script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yay!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, when I receive an email newsletter, gmail forwards it to the script. The script sends it back to me with nice clean URLs. Once again, I can see where links lead to before I decide whether to click.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tracking parameters (ie. &lt;code&gt;utm_*&lt;/code&gt;) and tracking pixels are removed as well. (I don&amp;rsquo;t care strongly about this but it was easy to add so I did.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;email-cleaner&#34;&gt;Email Cleaner&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For lack of a better name, I&amp;rsquo;m calling it &lt;strong&gt;Email Cleaner&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;It cleans crap from email newsletters&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Alternatively, I considered calling it &amp;lsquo;&lt;strong&gt;UntrackMe: Remove tracking from email newsletters&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rsquo;. Which sounds better?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m letting others try it. Maybe other people find it useful too. If there&amp;rsquo;s enough interest, I&amp;rsquo;ll turn it into a proper side project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;getting-started&#34;&gt;Getting started&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To try Email Cleaner, forward an email newsletter to &lt;code&gt;email-cleaner@bengtan.com&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a minute or two, you should get the newsletter sent back to you (from &lt;code&gt;no-reply@bengtan.com&lt;/code&gt;) with cleaned links and tracking pixels removed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you decide you like it, you can set up your email program to automatically forward email newsletters to &lt;code&gt;email-cleaner@bengtan.com&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How you do this depends on your email program so you&amp;rsquo;ll have to work it out youself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Please don&amp;rsquo;t set up your email program to automatically delete after forwarding. Since this is a new service, it&amp;rsquo;s a good idea to retain the original emails in case something goes wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;forwarding-loops&#34;&gt;Forwarding loops&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your automatic forwarding configuration mistakenly forwards the cleaned email (from Email Cleaner) back to Email Cleaner, it will detect this and send you an email with the message &amp;ldquo;Infinite loop detected&amp;rdquo;. If you get such an email, please adjust your forwarding configuration so you don&amp;rsquo;t forward cleaned emails to Email Cleaner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you use gmail (like I do), this can be accomplished by adding the condition &lt;code&gt;-subject:[email-cleaner]&lt;/code&gt; to your forwarding filter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-it-works&#34;&gt;How it works&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email Cleaner works as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It scans the email for links which match the following regular expressions:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34; data-lang=&#34;js&#34;&gt;	&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;\.list-manage\.com/track/click&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,
	&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;//click\.convertkit-mail\.com/&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,
	&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;//email\.substack.*/c/&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,
	&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;//apple\.co/&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,
	&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;//t\.co/&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If a link matches, then it&amp;rsquo;s a tracking link. Email Cleaner crawls the link to see if it&amp;rsquo;s a 3xx redirect. If it is, then the link is replaced by the destination URL.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any URL query parameters which are &lt;code&gt;mc_cid&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;mc_eid&lt;/code&gt;, or start with &lt;code&gt;utm_&lt;/code&gt; are also removed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then, Email Cleaner scans the email for tracking pixels. If any are found, it removes them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, the email is sent back to the sender.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email Cleaner is quite safe and conservative. It will only crawl links which are obviously tracking links.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email Cleaner currently handles three major mailing list service providers (MailChimp, ConvertKit, Substack). I&amp;rsquo;d happily add more. Just let me know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that Email Cleaner doesn&amp;rsquo;t magically bypass the tracking links. Instead, it triggers all of them from a data centre somewhere. It&amp;rsquo;s privacy-by-obfuscation instead of privacy-by-abstention. But it does prevent your web browser/IP address/location from being leaked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;benefits&#34;&gt;Benefits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Email newsletters are more user friendly. (I&amp;rsquo;m more inclined to click on a link if I see it&amp;rsquo;s a reputable website.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Helps detect phishing attacks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better user privacy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plain text emails are readable again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;plain-text-emails&#34;&gt;Plain text emails&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last benefit was an unexpected side effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whilst writing Email Cleaner, I discovered that plain text versions of email newsletters are completely unreadable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most agree that the term Artificial Intelligence was codified at a Dartmouth workshop in 1956 [httр://email.substack.com/c/eJxdkc-OgyAQh5-m3Grkr3rgsJd9DQM4WlIFA2O7vv1O2-xlE2CSHzPhy0dwCEsup91zRfY6Rjx3sAmegAiF7BsUE71mvZJcKUa87qgTgpG4mVAAXjYuGssOZN3dEkeLMafPBpOMzFp1wluppHM9Z2FoQQQbnAqd8tx2A7_P2t1HSCNoeEM5cwKy6Blx3R7868F-qkFqjviMK_hom1ym2rrqmr5twVfecTZHLs9tziuJmrWMtqy6kJ0cGtrYoFoF1Aou-ShpCHRsnac9d4wz4MNDtNvuNrTjkzbwu1YNCaNd3hGOZsykaAdpQptonZyur2v3dT1tan7tKeJpIFm3gL954I31Q8hMkKBU3N5Y1FRR3vdc9P2guhtABcZZx2ilTKoOn-tW0v90_AEVdJLl]. At a conference five years earlier [httр://email.substack.com/c/eJxdkEtuhDAMhk8zWSLyBBZZVKp6jSghDkTDJCiYody-YdhV8kO2bPn3N1qEKZdTr3lDcgWD5wo6wbEtdQVEKOyoUMY4WdEbLY0RbLId90oJFus4F4DNxdViOYDth19jcBhzek8ILdjNDk5xrQxozWenoTNmkL2cvQoimFaZz7PumCKkABYeUM6cgK32hrjXi_y6iG9aIW_7QUS3WJGQm1wWSv2aXwVvMd1jWq7O5wOvmwsUQL26NF3_7qiNRStawVtBW-lODw1v3GxaA9wpqWUgxpmH1k-8l15IAXK4qLYevqILd97Az05sCaNbHxGeTcisWA9pQZc4dS4vG5RuLxkj1e1IEc8RkvMrTB9P-NH9NjcukKDQN0yjQ8sNl30vVd8PpvuIIZFSdIKTfUYcU6apZP9x_AIL9Jrk], however, the concepts were discussed in detail, just not named. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is that supposed to be readable?! (It&amp;rsquo;s not just Substack. The other providers are almost just as bad.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email Cleaner changes it to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most agree that the term Artificial Intelligence was codified at a Dartmouth workshop in 1956 [httрs://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dartmouth_workshop]. At a conference five years earlier [httрs://computerhistory.org/blog/thinking-about-machines-and-thinking/], however, the concepts were discussed in detail, just not named. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which is moderately readable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be even better if it was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most agree that the term Artificial Intelligence was codified at a Dartmouth workshop in 1956 [0]. At a conference five years earlier [1], however, the concepts were discussed in detail, just not named. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[0] httрs://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dartmouth_workshop&lt;br /&gt;
[1] httрs://computerhistory.org/blog/thinking-about-machines-and-thinking/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;but that&amp;rsquo;s a story for another time. (I don&amp;rsquo;t know if it&amp;rsquo;s worth the effort to do this. Do many people still read emails in plain text?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;caveats&#34;&gt;Caveats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please note that Email Cleaner is only a proof of concept. It&amp;rsquo;s an experiment. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t even call it an MVP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s useful to me, but I don&amp;rsquo;t know if it&amp;rsquo;s useful for others. I&amp;rsquo;d like to find out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know how long Email Cleaner will last since:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s vulnerable to spam (There&amp;rsquo;s no authentication or access control), and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not scalable (It&amp;rsquo;s running on a tiny server).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the spam bots arrive, or too many people use it, it&amp;rsquo;ll probably have to stop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or if there&amp;rsquo;s sufficient interest, I&amp;rsquo;ll rewrite it into a proper side project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;privacy&#34;&gt;Privacy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please don&amp;rsquo;t forward any personal or private emails to Email Cleaner. Only forward publicly available email newsletters (Paid newsletters are okay).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All received emails go to Email Cleaner&amp;rsquo;s inbox. I hope to accumulate more test data with which to conduct further research on mailing list service providers and improve Email Cleaner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s not really a privacy policy. This is an experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you forward emails to Email Cleaner, I consider that as your opt-in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anything you forward to Email Cleaner could be used to improve Email Cleaner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OTOH, I don&amp;rsquo;t know anything about you anyway. All I have is an email address and what email newsletters you subscribe to (whatever can be inferred from that).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;feedback&#34;&gt;Feedback&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this is a new and experimental service, please don&amp;rsquo;t expect it to be perfectly reliable nor correct. If you forward an email to Email Cleaner and don&amp;rsquo;t get a reply in a few minutes, maybe something broke. Please get in touch with me and I&amp;rsquo;d be happy to look into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions, suggestions, criticisms, etc. — please also let me know. I&amp;rsquo;d be happy to talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you like Email Cleaner! Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Positioning isn&#39;t marketing. It&#39;s strategy</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/blog/positioning-isnt-marketing-its-strategy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Feb 2021 11:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/blog/positioning-isnt-marketing-its-strategy/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;I was reading &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aprildunford.com&#34;&gt;April Dunford&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s book &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aprildunford.com/obviously-awesome&#34;&gt;Obviously Awesome&lt;/a&gt; about product positioning and something struck me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought I was reading a marketing book. Somehow I ended up reading a business strategy book instead. (And a very good one too.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We engineers/developers/hackers/nerds tend to think of product positioning as something that &amp;lsquo;marketing&amp;rsquo; people do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as I read through the book, it dawns on me that positioning has a core relationship with business/product strategy. It tells us what business or product development should be working on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;* * *&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s try a thought experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A startup produces a new database that can quickly find something in a very large collection of data — much faster than the incumbent databases on the market at the time. They try to sell the database but struggle to compete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The startup pivots the database into a business intelligence tool. Suddenly they are competing against other business intelligence tools. Their product has a competitive advantage (ie. superior analysis capabilities) and sales takes off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does this sound like a marketing story? No, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s strategy. The startup discovers a new use case and successfully re-positions into a new market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s try another one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A startup produces cloud-based ad-supported accounting software for small business owners. After three years, they had over 500,000 business customers. However, advertising revenue alone isn&amp;rsquo;t enough to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The startup expands from accounting to financial services. They introduce new add-ons around their core product and charge fees for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shift is successful and helped them to grow to over 4 million customers. They were then acquired for $537 million dollars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, this is not a marketing story. This is a strategic re-positioning to target an adjacent market and capture more value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One more:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A startup produces a new enterprise CRM but struggles to compete against the incumbent CRM. They listen closely to one of their model customers (an investment bank) and focus on that market segment. The startup pivots to being &amp;lsquo;CRM for investment banks&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pivot is successful. A few years later, they are acquired by the incumbent CRM company for $1.4 billion dollars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The startup discovers a niche where it is successful and re-positions itself in that niche. (This is a &amp;lsquo;focus&amp;rsquo; strategy.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;* * *&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These stories are from the book. They are case studies about product positioning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But they&amp;rsquo;re not marketing stories. They&amp;rsquo;re stories about strategy and pivots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re building a product, you need to consider positioning. Positioning tells you what to focus on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t just leave positioning for &amp;lsquo;marketing&amp;rsquo; to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Positioning is not marketing. It&amp;rsquo;s strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open secrets about Hacker News</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/blog/open-secrets-hacker-news/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 12:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/blog/open-secrets-hacker-news/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;I spent a few days examining the mechanics of Hacker News (HN) and I discovered some open secrets. &amp;ldquo;Open&amp;rdquo; because they&amp;rsquo;re not private. &amp;ldquo;Secret&amp;rdquo; because they&amp;rsquo;re not well known. One of them can triple the chances of a story reaching the front page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are listed below with a sprinkling of my own analysis. Sources are included so you can explore further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sandbox-live-list-and-the-top30&#34;&gt;Sandbox, Live List, and the Top30&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three parts of Hacker News which I&amp;rsquo;m calling the Sandbox, the Live List and the Top30.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Top30 are the top 30 stories which appear on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/new&#34;&gt;front page&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com&#34;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;. Stories with more points/upvotes are ranked higher. Stories which are older are ranked lower. An algorithm balances these two factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Live List is the rest of the top stories after the Top30. These appear on &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/news?p=2&#34;&gt;page two&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/news?p=3&#34;&gt;three&lt;/a&gt; and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Sandbox is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/newest&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;new&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt; section and lists all stories ranked by time. Newer stories appear higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a new story is posted, it is listed only in the sandbox. Once (or if) it has 5 points, then it also appears in the Live List.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;making-the-front-page&#34;&gt;Making the front page&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A story needs to accumulate 5 points to appear in the Live List. Where it initially appears depends on how quickly it accumulated points. If points are acquired quickly enough, it appears high enough to be in the Top30. Otherwise, it appears at a lower position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once a story appears on the Live List, it will have more exposure and acquire more points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stories which begin life on the Live List on page two or three sometimes accumulate more points quickly enough to rise up to the Top30.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;upvote-conversion-rate&#34;&gt;Upvote conversion rate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The upvote conversion rate is the proportion of readers who upvote a story. It&amp;rsquo;s a proxy for how strongly a story appeals to readers. More interesting stories will have a higher rate of upvotes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether a story (acquires 5 points and) escapes the sandbox depends on the rate and the number of page views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Chance of escaping sandbox = upvote conversion rate ✕ views&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider an example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A newly submitted story will get around 30 page views from being listed in the Sandbox (The actual number varies so let&amp;rsquo;s just talk about averages). All stories start with one point. If it gets 4 additional upvotes, it will escape the Sandbox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, the story must persuade 13.3% or more of readers to upvote. That&amp;rsquo;s a pretty high conversion rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, most stories will rate much lower. Hence, some luck is needed: Either a transient boost in the conversion rate, or more page views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;timing&#34;&gt;Timing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Timing affects how many times a sandboxed story is viewed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Views = number of users online / rate of new submissions&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But timing is not predictable in a reliable way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Posting a story during a busy period means more viewers and more chances for upvotes. But there are also more newer stories that push it down the Sandbox ranking too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best time to post is when the ratio of viewers to new stories is highest. But no one knows with certainty when that happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the analysis is probabilistic. You are not guaranteed to get onto the front page just by submitting on at a high-probability time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are game-theoric implications; the more people submitting at a time (weekday mornings), the less likely people will see your post on /new before it is pushed off the first page, and it is highly unlikely to get upvotes once it has fallen off the top 30 slots. (hence the repost/second chance rules)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=11515207&#34;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=11515207&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/MdUvMB9.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;MdUvMB9.png&#34; alt=&#34;% of all Hacker News Submissions Which Receive 10+ Points&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;most-stories-fail&#34;&gt;Most stories &amp;lsquo;fail&amp;rsquo;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most stories &amp;lsquo;fail&amp;rsquo; and have only one or two points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The median is either 1 (no upvotes) or 2 (just 1 upvote)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=9864254&#34;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=9864254&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/SN5BuAJ.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;SN5BuAJ.png&#34; alt=&#34;Median Score of all Hacker News Submissions&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=9864254&#34;&gt;If your HN submission doesn&amp;rsquo;t get any upvotes, don&amp;rsquo;t worry about it&lt;/a&gt;. Don&amp;rsquo;t take it personally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=tptacek&#34;&gt;tptacek&lt;/a&gt; is one of the most well-known users on Hacker News. He has a &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=23458896&#34;&gt;pretty good track record of getting blog posts on the front page&lt;/a&gt; yet his &amp;lsquo;success&amp;rsquo; rate is around 50%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;re-posting&#34;&gt;Re-posting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hacker News allows re-posts. This is not widely known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a story has not had significant attention in the last year or so, a small number of reposts is ok. Otherwise we bury reposts as duplicates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/newsfaq.html&#34;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/newsfaq.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Albeit, a &amp;lsquo;small number&amp;rsquo; is not defined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I&amp;rsquo;d stay at 3. I&amp;rsquo;d also wait at least a day between re-posts (and try re-posting at different time slots).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Re-posting can triple-or-more the chances of a story reaching the front page.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a story that was posted six times:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://hn.algolia.com/?dateRange=all&amp;amp;page=0&amp;amp;prefix=false&amp;amp;query=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.lihaoyi.com%2Fpost%2FFromFirstPrinciplesWhyScala.html&amp;amp;sort=byDate&amp;amp;type=story&#34;&gt;https://hn.algolia.com/?dateRange=all&amp;amp;page=0&amp;amp;prefix=false&amp;amp;query=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.lihaoyi.com%2Fpost%2FFromFirstPrinciplesWhyScala.html&amp;amp;sort=byDate&amp;amp;type=story&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;dont-delete-and-re-post&#34;&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t delete and re-post&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flip-side of re-posting is that delete-and-repost is not allowed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please don&amp;rsquo;t delete and repost the same story. Deletion is for things that shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have been submitted in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/newsfaq.html&#34;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/newsfaq.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;pg has said that this is a ban worthy offense. And I still see people doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=6861740&#34;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=6861740&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;text-posts-are-penalised&#34;&gt;Text posts are penalised&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Submissions which are text and lack a URL (sometimes called a &amp;lsquo;self post&amp;rsquo;) have a ranking penalty applied. The factor has been estimated to be a 0.4 or 0.7 multiplier. (Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=1076633&#34;&gt;Why you should submit your stuff as a blog posting&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you must post text, consider posting a link and then submit the text as a comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Posts without URLs get penalized, so you&amp;rsquo;d be better off posting this with a link, then adding your text as a first comment in the new thread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=21874086&#34;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=21874086&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;show-hn&#34;&gt;Show HN&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Show HN section of Hacker News also has a &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/shownew&#34;&gt;sandbox&lt;/a&gt; and it&amp;rsquo;s own live &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/show&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;Show&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt; listing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every Show HN appears on shownew. Once it clears a small points threshold, it will appear on the show page in the top bar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/showhn.html&#34;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/showhn.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I don&amp;rsquo;t know what the points threshold for Show HN is.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A story which is posted to &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/showhn.html&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;Show HN&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt; appears in both sandboxes and has more opportunities to be upvoted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;karma&#34;&gt;Karma&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=23458656&#34;&gt;Do posts by authors with more karma rank higher?&lt;/a&gt; The answer is: No.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;escape-velocity&#34;&gt;Escape velocity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking into account all of the above:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Chance of escaping sandbox = re-posts ✕ upvote conversion rate ✕ number of users online / rate of new submissions&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;second-chance-pool&#34;&gt;Second chance pool&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A small proportion of interesting stories which didn&amp;rsquo;t attract enough upvotes are curated by the moderators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is taken out of the sandbox and it&amp;rsquo;s timestamp is artifically manipulated so it appears in the second half of the Top30. From there, it decays normally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moderators and a small number of reviewer users comb the depths of /newest looking for stories that got overlooked but which the community might find interesting. Those go into a second-chance pool from which stories are randomly selected and lobbed onto the bottom part of the front page. This guarantees them a few minutes of attention. If they don&amp;rsquo;t interest the community they soon fall off, but if they do, they get upvoted and stay on the front page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=11662380&#34;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=11662380&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The implication? The Top30 is a combination of organically-upvoted stories and moderator-boosted stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;vote-manipulation&#34;&gt;Vote manipulation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hacker News has software to detect vote manipulation (ie. asking friends to upvote).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=22761897&#34;&gt;Voting ring detection has been one of HN&amp;rsquo;s priorities for over 12 years&lt;/a&gt; and it&amp;rsquo;s pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HN&amp;rsquo;s anti-voting-ring software is now so strict that the main thing we have to do is turn it off when a submission is good enough&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=15511238&#34;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=15511238&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you get past the voting ring detector, you won&amp;rsquo;t get past the readers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hacker News readers are very protective of the site. Stories which reach the Top30 via dubious means attract intense scrutiny. Sometimes even organically-upvoted stories are suspected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;readers reacted negatively, even violently, to seeing junk on HN&amp;rsquo;s front page. By &amp;ldquo;junk&amp;rdquo; I mean stories that were placed there randomly and that weren&amp;rsquo;t of high-enough quality to otherwise be credible candidates for the front page. Basically, it was an &amp;ldquo;ow my eyes&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;get that shit away from me&amp;rdquo; effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HN users have an intense emotional relationship with the front page&lt;/strong&gt;. This shows up in the inevitable &amp;ldquo;How is this on HN?&amp;rdquo; comments when a story somehow violates the commenter&amp;rsquo;s personal contract or mental model of HN. &amp;hellip; lessons I drew from that experience: (1) people&amp;rsquo;s relationship with HN is surprisingly personal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=21868928&#34;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=21868928&lt;/a&gt; (emphasis added)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;dang&#34;&gt;dang&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hacker News is moderated mainly by &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=dang&#34;&gt;dang&lt;/a&gt; aka Dan Gackle (pronounced &amp;lsquo;Gackley&amp;rsquo;). He&amp;rsquo;s not of asian descent. But &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20643264&#34;&gt;he&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25054045&#34;&gt;is&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25049415&#34;&gt;the&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25049119&#34;&gt;best&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25056408&#34;&gt;moderator&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25048958&#34;&gt;in&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25051566&#34;&gt;the&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25052249&#34;&gt;world&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;random&#34;&gt;Random&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story &amp;lsquo;Learn Git Branching&amp;rsquo; has been posted almost 20 times across &lt;a href=&#34;http://pcottle.github.io/learnGitBranching/&#34;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://learngitbranching.js.org/&#34;&gt;urls&lt;/a&gt;. The distribution of points is &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/from?site=pcottle.github.io&#34;&gt;pretty&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/from?site=learngitbranching.js.org&#34;&gt;random&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-reading&#34;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/minimaxir/hacker-news-undocumented&#34;&gt;A List of Hacker News&amp;rsquo;s Undocumented Features and Behaviors&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newyorker.com/news/letter-from-silicon-valley/the-lonely-work-of-moderating-hacker-news&#34;&gt;The Lonely Work of Moderating Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20643052&#34;&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt; and more &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25048415&#34;&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cheeaun/awesome-hacker-news&#34;&gt;Awesome Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; - A collection of awesome Hacker News apps, libraries, resources and shiny things&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My go-to tool for reading long JSON snippets</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/blog/reading-long-json-snippets/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 12:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/blog/reading-long-json-snippets/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.json.org/json-en.html&#34;&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt; is ubiquitous and I often run into it whilst developing or debugging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it&amp;rsquo;s in raw form like this &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;plaintext.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;screenshot: json as raw text&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s hard for a human to interpret.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For small snippets, I could copy-and-paste it into a text file and hand-prettify it. For long snippets, that&amp;rsquo;s obviously not scalable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stumbled upon a very useful tool for interpreting and analysing (extremely) long JSON snippets. The surprising thing is that it&amp;rsquo;s been around for a long time and I just never noticed. However, once I knew about it, I kept using it, and it&amp;rsquo;s now my go-to tool for analysing long JSON snippets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tool?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mozilla Firefox.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, the web browser. (It also helps that Firefox is my main browser.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a link to a random JSON file from the internet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bengtan/bengtan.github.io/main/content/css-named-colours-picker/dist/main.js.map&#34;&gt;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bengtan/bengtan.github.io/main/content/css-named-colours-picker/dist/main.js.map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you click on the link with Firefox you get something human-unfriendly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;plaintext.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;screenshot: json as raw text&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if you open a file with a &lt;code&gt;.json&lt;/code&gt; extension on your local computer , you get &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;json.png&#34; alt=&#34;screenshot: json in firefox json browser&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; which is a nice and useful and human-friendly json browser with collapsible sections, pretty printing and &lt;strong&gt;filtering&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I think Firefox shows the json browser when the mimetype is set to json, and opening a local file with a &lt;code&gt;.json&lt;/code&gt; extension is an easy way to set the mimetype.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stumbled upon this by chance. But since then, everytime I have a long JSON snippet to debug, I save it to a text file, give it a &lt;code&gt;.json&lt;/code&gt; extension and open it with Firefox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;* * *&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so installing Firefox just to browse JSON is probably overkill, but this is great for me since I already use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m glad Firefox is my main browser.&lt;/p&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A recipe for recreating the functionality of Web SQL</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/blog/recipe-for-websql/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2021 12:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/blog/recipe-for-websql/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Firstly, let&amp;rsquo;s step back briefly in history.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.w3.org/TR/webdatabase/&#34;&gt;Web SQL&lt;/a&gt; was a way for javascript (and web apps) to use a relational database (specifically, &lt;a href=&#34;http://sqlite.org&#34;&gt;sqlite&lt;/a&gt;) that was stored in the web browser (ie. client side). It was popular amongst front-end developers for a while as it was a convenient and powerful method for storing and manipulating complex data in the browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, for various reasons, it didn&amp;rsquo;t become a web standard and was discontinued in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite it being a long time ago now, every once in a while, someone will still lament that Web SQL had to die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Back to the present&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I write &lt;a href=&#34;http://gigobooks.com&#34;&gt;Gig&amp;rsquo;o&amp;rsquo;Books&lt;/a&gt; and the initial version of it stored user data in an sqlite file on the local computer. Since it was desktop software, this is nothing unusual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later, however, I wanted to port Gig&amp;rsquo;o&amp;rsquo;Books to the web, and so, I needed a way to run sqlite on the client-side web, in the browser. I found &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/sql-js/sql.js&#34;&gt;sql.js&lt;/a&gt; which, thanks to the magic of WebAssembly, works very well. Extremely well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web edition of Gig&amp;rsquo;o&amp;rsquo;Books managed user data in an sqlite database in the browser&amp;rsquo;s javascript runtime. However, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t persisted. Every time the user refreshed the browser, they needed to load their data anew by &amp;lsquo;opening&amp;rsquo; a file on their local computer (assuming that they had saved the data previously). This was by design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it wasn&amp;rsquo;t good enough. Subsequent user feedback indicated that the database did need to be persisted across browser sessions. Otherwise, it was too easy to accidentally lose data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I looked around for an easy and simple way to persist the sqlite database and I found IDB-Keyval. &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/jakearchibald/idb-keyval&#34;&gt;IDB-Keyval&lt;/a&gt; allows simple key-value pairs to be stored in browser storage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I experimented with storing the entire database (ie. as a serialised string/binary) as a single key-value. After playing around with it, performance seemed fine. It didn&amp;rsquo;t feel noticeably slow or anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I went with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;* * *&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a while, I thought back about what had been done &amp;hellip; Wait, did I just recreate Web SQL? 🤔&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, sort of. It&amp;rsquo;s not exactly the same but it&amp;rsquo;s good enough &amp;hellip; Actually. It&amp;rsquo;s. Quite. Good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I guess &amp;hellip; Yes I did, I did just recreate Web SQL. Web SQL is alive!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;* * *&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what if you want to do this too?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I don&amp;rsquo;t have generic full working code to give out. The web edition of Gig&amp;rsquo;o&amp;rsquo;Books waits for the user to click &amp;lsquo;recover&amp;rsquo; before loading the sqlite database from indexedDB and that&amp;rsquo;s probably not what you want in your app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I can give you a recipe that I&amp;rsquo;m certain will work, and I can reveal some snippets from the source code of the web edition of Gig&amp;rsquo;o&amp;rsquo;Books. Implementing the rest is an exercise for the reader. 🙂&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tinkering with it is also encouraged. 🙂&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;recipe&#34;&gt;Recipe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use sql.js to create an sqlite database and do stuff with it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whenever there is a change to the database, export it from sql.js and save a snapshot to indexedDB.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the page or webapp is loaded by the browser, inspect indexedDB to see if there is a saved snapshot. If there is, then load the snapshot into sql.js.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that we are not writing and reading indexedDB for every change to the database. It&amp;rsquo;s writing only when there is a change, yes, but reading only when the page or webapp is loaded. Furthermore, the writes can be throttled for better performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effectively, indexedDB is an infrequently used mostly-write cache.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further details are below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that code snippets are from (the web edition of) Gig&amp;rsquo;o&amp;rsquo;Books verbatim and contain Gig&amp;rsquo;o&amp;rsquo;Books-specific references. They won&amp;rsquo;t work out-of-the-box with other code. You&amp;rsquo;ll have to extract out the important parts and integrate into your own code yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, some code snippets are typescript instead of vanilla javascript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;detecting-a-change-and-calling-a-handler&#34;&gt;Detecting a change and calling a handler&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any query which starts with one of &lt;code&gt;[&#39;insert&#39;, &#39;del&#39;, &#39;delete&#39;, &#39;update&#39;]&lt;/code&gt; and results in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sql-js/sql.js/blob/36859494d53f1962f2059d9597782f5f4ab49172/src/api.js#L1092&#34;&gt;.getRowsModified()&lt;/a&gt; returning positive constitutes a change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34; data-lang=&#34;js&#34;&gt;            &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;// This code is from the knex dialect for sql.js
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;            &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;// getRowsModified() is only applicable for insert, update and delete
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;            &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;rowsAffected&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;lowerSql&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;obj&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;sql&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;trim&lt;/span&gt;().&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;toLowerCase&lt;/span&gt;()
            ;[&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;insert&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;del&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;delete&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;update&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;].&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;forEach&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;op&lt;/span&gt; =&amp;gt; {
                &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;lowerSql&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;startsWith&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;`&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;op&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt; `&lt;/span&gt;)) {
                    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;rowsAffected&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;obj&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;connection&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;getRowsModified&lt;/span&gt;()
                }
            })

            &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;// Notify upstream if any rows were changed
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;            &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;rowsAffected&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;obj&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;options&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;skipOnChange&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;obj&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;sql&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;indexOf&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;knex_migrations_lock&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;config&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;onChange&lt;/span&gt;) {
                &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;config&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;onChange&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;obj&lt;/span&gt;)
            }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;If there is a change, then trigger a call to a change handler:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ts&#34; data-lang=&#34;ts&#34;&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;onChange() {&lt;/span&gt;
        ...

        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;// Trigger out of band: Since snapshot() interacts with the DB, it&amp;#39;s not
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;// good practice to have it occur within a DB-triggered handler
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;// Throttle: If multiple changes happen, only call snapshot() once at the end
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;timeoutId&lt;/span&gt;) {
            &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;clearTimeout&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;timeoutId&lt;/span&gt;)
        }
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;timeoutId&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;setTimeout&lt;/span&gt;(() &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; {
            &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;snapshot&lt;/span&gt;()
            &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;timeoutId&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
        }, &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1000&lt;/span&gt;)
    }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;snapshot()&lt;/code&gt; calls are throttled (&lt;code&gt;snapshot()&lt;/code&gt; is defined below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since a single user-initiated action can result in multiple changes to the database, &lt;code&gt;snapshot()&lt;/code&gt; is only called (ie. database is persisted to indexedDB) after all the changes are done. A debouncing period of 1000 milliseconds works well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;creating-and-loading-snapshots&#34;&gt;Creating and loading snapshots&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the code from Gig&amp;rsquo;o&amp;rsquo;Books that interacts with indexedDB via IDB-Keyval.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ts&#34; data-lang=&#34;ts&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;// snapshot.ts
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; { &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;SqlJs&lt;/span&gt; } &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;sql.js/module&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;Idb&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;idb-keyval&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; { &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;Project&lt;/span&gt; } &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;../core&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;SNAPSHOT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;snapshot&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;type&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;Snapshot&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; {
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;filename&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;timestamp&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;Date&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;mru&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;Uint8Array&lt;/span&gt;
}

&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;async&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;snapshot() {&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;database&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;SqlJs.Database&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;Project&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;database&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;any&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;// typecast
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;Snapshot&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; {
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;Project.variables.get&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;title&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;),
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;filename&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;Project.project&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;filename&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;timestamp&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; Date(),
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;mru&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;window.location.hash.substring&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;),
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;database.export&lt;/span&gt;()
    }
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;await&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;Idb&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;set&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;SNAPSHOT&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;)
}

&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;getSnapshot&lt;/span&gt;()&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;Promise&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;Snapshot&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt; {
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;Idb&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;SNAPSHOT&lt;/span&gt;)
}

&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;deleteSnapshot&lt;/span&gt;()&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;Promise&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;any&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt; {
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;Idb&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;del&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;SNAPSHOT&lt;/span&gt;)
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Again, this is code directly from Gig&amp;rsquo;o&amp;rsquo;Books and won&amp;rsquo;t work out of the box for your app. Don&amp;rsquo;t worry about &lt;code&gt;Project&lt;/code&gt; nor &lt;code&gt;.title&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;.filename&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;.timestamp&lt;/code&gt; nor &lt;code&gt;.mru&lt;/code&gt;. These are all Gig&amp;rsquo;o&amp;rsquo;Books-specific things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The important field is &lt;code&gt;.data&lt;/code&gt; which holds the database in serialised form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see this source file is very very simple. It&amp;rsquo;s basically just a thin wrapper around &lt;code&gt;Idb.set(), Idb.get(), Idb.del()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During page load or webapp initialisation, create a database from the snapshot (if exists) by doing something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34; data-lang=&#34;js&#34;&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;snapshot&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;getSnapshot&lt;/span&gt;()
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;snapshot&lt;/span&gt;) {
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;database&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;Database&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;snapshot&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;)
        ...
    }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;knex&#34;&gt;Knex&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the code snippets reference &lt;a href=&#34;http://knexjs.org/&#34;&gt;knex&lt;/a&gt; (which is a popular and useful database abstraction/ORM-like layer) because Gig&amp;rsquo;o&amp;rsquo;Books uses knex over sql.js.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you use knex, please note that knex&amp;rsquo;s built-in sqlite driver (which knex calls a &amp;lsquo;dialect&amp;rsquo;) is meant to be used against &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/mapbox/node-sqlite3&#34;&gt;node-sqlite3&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s API and doesn&amp;rsquo;t work with sql.js.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I wrote a customised sql.js dialect for knex so Gig&amp;rsquo;o&amp;rsquo;Books could use it.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;demo-and-outcome&#34;&gt;Demo and outcome&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to see (something very similar to) this recipe working, head to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://gigobooks.com/webapp&#34;&gt;Gig&amp;rsquo;o&amp;rsquo;Books webapp&lt;/a&gt; and play around with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open up the Storage tab in your browser&amp;rsquo;s developer tools and look at the indexedDB items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everytime you make a change, notice that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An asterisk appears next to the browser window/tab title (to indicate an unsaved change), and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The snapshot that is cached in indexedDB changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How well does this work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Gig&amp;rsquo;o&amp;rsquo;Books, it works quite well (Feel free to try to break Gig&amp;rsquo;o&amp;rsquo;Books 🙂). Exporting into indexedDB is quite quick relative to humans, and also relatively infrequent. Performance feels good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I admit I didn&amp;rsquo;t actually measure the overhead.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your webapp has a very large sqlite data file, maybe the overhead of export-and-persist might be too much. YMMV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;discussion-and-future-directions&#34;&gt;Discussion and future directions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I created this solution for myself, I didn&amp;rsquo;t know about some existing alternatives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/Philzen/WebSQL-Polyfill&#34;&gt;http://github.com/Philzen/WebSQL-Polyfill&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/yathit/ydn-db&#34;&gt;http://github.com/yathit/ydn-db&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;but I&amp;rsquo;m happy with this solution anyway. It&amp;rsquo;s very simple to understand, it&amp;rsquo;s transparent, and it&amp;rsquo;s easy to both build and customise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I didn&amp;rsquo;t have generic full working code to publish. It was either post about this without full code, or not post about it at all. I chose the former.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Possible future work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Package up the recipe into a generic module,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publish the knex dialect for sql.js that Gig&amp;rsquo;o&amp;rsquo;Books uses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll see. Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;one-more-thing&#34;&gt;One more thing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you work with sqlite, remember to &lt;a href=&#34;https://sqlite.org/lang_vacuum.html&#34;&gt;VACUUM&lt;/a&gt; once in a while.&lt;/p&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>App Startup vs Content Startup</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/blog/app-startup-vs-content-startup/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2021 12:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/blog/app-startup-vs-content-startup/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;Here is something that occurred to me recently. It&amp;rsquo;s not a law or anything, but just a thought-provoking observation. I find it interesting, and maybe it&amp;rsquo;s useful as a tool in thinking about startups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most startups are either an &lt;strong&gt;app startup&lt;/strong&gt; or a &lt;strong&gt;content startup&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do I mean? Let&amp;rsquo;s back up a bit and talk about definitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I say &amp;lsquo;startup&amp;rsquo;, I don&amp;rsquo;t mean a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.paulgraham.com/growth.html&#34;&gt;company that is designed to grow fast&lt;/a&gt;. I mean any venture that is new (and, in the context of this discussion, usually related to tech).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An app startup (where &amp;lsquo;app&amp;rsquo; == &amp;lsquo;application&amp;rsquo; and doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean just smartphone apps) is something that sells a technology (or an integration of existing technologies). It allows users to do something new, or do something in a faster, better or cheaper way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A content startup is something that sells content, or sells the ability to interact with other people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With definitions out of the way, let me repeat the above statement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most startups are either an app startup or a content startup.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, in truth, all businesses do a bit of both, but usually, a startup is dominated by one or the other. Hence, conceptually, most startups can be classified as one or the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Note that I said &amp;lsquo;most&amp;rsquo;, not &amp;lsquo;all&amp;rsquo;. This is just a heuristic, and sometimes heuristics break down.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Off the top of my head, here are some &lt;strong&gt;app startups&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google search&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Android&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tesla&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open AI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Substack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WordPress, Ghost, or any other CMS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These startups produce and/or sell a technology. Usually, the technology is novel or not easy to reproduce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some &lt;strong&gt;content startups&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BetaList&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product Hunt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stratechery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Substack newsletter writers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone who sells eBooks, courses, or newsletters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tech media ie. Engadget, Techmeme etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone who sells themes or plugins for WordPress or another CMS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AirBnB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Twitter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Content startups utilise known technology. Their technology is reproducible but the value of the startup is not in the technology. Instead, the hard-to-reproduce part is in the content side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, it&amp;rsquo;s not hard to recreate the functionality of BetaList, Product Hunt or Stratechery, but it is much harder to duplicate the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, anyone can sell WordPress themes online. However, it&amp;rsquo;s much harder to create themes that people want to buy and to generate enough marketing and exposure to consistently get new buyers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, anyone can create an AirBnB or Twitter clone, but they&amp;rsquo;d be useless without a community of users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What startups can you think of? Are they app startups or content startups?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bonus/trick question: Can you think of any startups which aren&amp;rsquo;t easily classified by this distinction?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;* * *&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s the point of thinking of startups as either app or content?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it&amp;rsquo;s fun and frivolous theorising and it could be a useful aid in thinking about startups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me personally, it leads to a very important and relevant insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that &amp;hellip; people who are makers/builders tend to build app startups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(What about the reverse? Do non-technical founders tend to build content startups? Um, I don&amp;rsquo;t know. Maybe this is a question for a future article.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I like building things. As a developer/maker/hacker/whatever, I always gravitate towards app startup ideas. I instinctively try to build some cool new tech. I have never, in the past, considered content startup ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a blind spot. It&amp;rsquo;s a very big blind spot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am unconsciously cutting myself off from half of the market of startup ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yikes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All those stories about people who produce courses on how to use the next hip new tech stack and sell for thousands of dollars per month? I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be able to conceive doing something similar because I&amp;rsquo;ve blinded myself to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily for me, I&amp;rsquo;m aware of this now. Hopefully it&amp;rsquo;s not going to limit me any more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about you? If you are also a maker/hacker and you only consider app startup ideas, are you also limiting yourself?&lt;/p&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A New Beginning</title>
      <link>https://bengtan.com/blog/a-new-beginning/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2021 12:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bengtan.com/blog/a-new-beginning/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;This blog represents a new beginning and I&amp;rsquo;m both excited and trepidatious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, I&amp;rsquo;ve considered blogging at one time or another over the last 15-20 years, but I&amp;rsquo;ve always been too busy with more important or fun &amp;lsquo;stuff&amp;rsquo;. Everytime I think about it, it sounds like a great idea &amp;hellip; and then it fizzles out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a history of building things. Software/tech/web things that are supposed to make money. Call them micro-startups or side projects or lifestyle businesses or whatever. I&amp;rsquo;ve done a smattering of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from jobs and freelancing gigs, I would spend my discretionary time on building something &amp;hellip; that I hoped would make money. It&amp;rsquo;s great fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except when they don&amp;rsquo;t make money. Then it&amp;rsquo;s just a time sink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the things that I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to monetise, sometimes the results were modest. Other times, the results were mediocre or downright terrible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my most recent project, I wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gigobooks.com&#34;&gt;non-subscription accounting app&lt;/a&gt; for people with gigs or simple affairs. I had a lot of fun writing it. And I use it for myself (ie. dogfooding) too. Awesome!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve spent the better part of nine months building it and I&amp;rsquo;ve shipped the MVP. Problem is &amp;hellip; Where are my users?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uh, oh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s happened again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I built something. And the users aren&amp;rsquo;t coming. Even worse, this time, they don&amp;rsquo;t even know about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have tried to get some word out and I&amp;rsquo;ve posted on various forums over the Internet. I&amp;rsquo;ve got a tiny trickle of people who visit the website and then, AFAICT, don&amp;rsquo;t come back. That&amp;rsquo;s about it. No one (other than myself) is actually using the app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Granted, I didn&amp;rsquo;t spend a lot of time doing &amp;lsquo;marketing&amp;rsquo; things, but I did spend &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; time, and the results have been underwhelming. It also doesn&amp;rsquo;t help that I have no pre-existing audience. No blog, no twitter followers. Nada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Distribution is a hard problem. Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s sometimes even harder than writing software. Lack of distribution has killed my previous projects before. Several times. If I don&amp;rsquo;t solve this problem, it&amp;rsquo;s going to kill this latest project too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I took a step back and thought about things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;* * *&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I need to learn how to do distribution. And marketing and all that other stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can build things, but if I can&amp;rsquo;t reach users, then what&amp;rsquo;s the point?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my to-do list of marketing activities, I had &amp;lsquo;content marketing&amp;rsquo; ie. writing articles and blogging. Maybe I should jump straight to it and give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A related thought &amp;hellip; There are numerous posts on the Internet about people who are making X thousands of dollars N months after launching, or they do a kickstarter project and smash through the funding target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The common thread? They already had an email newsletter of 3000 readers, or they had 10000 twitter followers, or they were already a well-known member of an existing forum, or something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if I want to solve distribution, I&amp;rsquo;m gonna need something like that. I need people who are reading what I&amp;rsquo;m writing. I need to interact with people who I can bounce ideas off. I need people who I can reach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright. Fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s give this content-marketing/blogging thing a try. Let&amp;rsquo;s learn more about &amp;lsquo;marketing stuff&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let&amp;rsquo;s not just read about it. Let&amp;rsquo;s do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;m gonna write a blog, get some practical experience at content marketing, and see how things go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either it&amp;rsquo;s going to work: The next time I launch a new project, it will be more likely to succeed as I&amp;rsquo;ll be better at distribution (hopefully).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or it&amp;rsquo;s not going to work: I should stop building things and concentrate on paid work instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;* * *&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;m gonna write a blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let&amp;rsquo;s refine the idea a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t want to do something where I&amp;rsquo;m blatantly blogging just to monetise or to push a sale. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to be a shill for my next project (whatever that might be). It&amp;rsquo;s not all just about money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to write about stuff I&amp;rsquo;m interested in (Software, technology, startups, life, etc.). Otherwise it&amp;rsquo;ll turn in a drag and I&amp;rsquo;ll lose motivation. There has to be some intrinsic value in it too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having opened my mind to the idea of blogging, I&amp;rsquo;ve suddenly had a lot of ideas for things to write about. Things that my subconscious has always wanted to talk about but never got the chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m excited. Yes, it&amp;rsquo;s new and very different from building things, but it sounds like it could be fun too. (I&amp;rsquo;m also a little nervous) Hopefully, it also turns out well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent most of nine months writing Gig&amp;rsquo;o&amp;rsquo;Books. Imagine if I spent nine months blogging. I wonder what the results would be? Only one way to find out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here I am. A new beginning. Let&amp;rsquo;s do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wish me luck!&lt;/p&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
